<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New observations upon the decalogue: or The second of the four parts of Christian doctrine, preached upon the catechism. By John Despagne Minister of the Gospel</title>
            <title>Novelles observations sur le decalogue. English.</title>
            <author>Espagne, Jean d', 1591-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3263A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829018</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33453</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33453)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1986:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>New observations upon the decalogue: or The second of the four parts of Christian doctrine, preached upon the catechism. By John Despagne Minister of the Gospel</title>
                  <title>Novelles observations sur le decalogue. English.</title>
                  <author>Espagne, Jean d', 1591-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 176, 167-173, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Newcomb, for Joshuah Kirton, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Kings Arms in Pauls-Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An English translation of: Espagne, Jean d'.  Novelles observations sur le decalogue.</note>
                  <note>With nine preliminary contents leaves.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Magdalene College Library, Cambridge.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:1"/>
            <p>NEW Obſervations UPON THE DECALOGUE: OR The Second of the Four Parts OF Chriſtian Doctrine, Preached upon the CATECHISM.</p>
            <p>By JOHN DESPAGNE Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> for <hi>Joſhuah Kirton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the Kings Arms in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:2"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT HONORABLE and THRICE-ILLUSTRIOUS PHILIP Earl of PEMBROKE and MONT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COMERY, Baron of SHURLAND, Lord of CARDIFFE, PARR, ROS and KEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAL, MARMYON and S. QUINTIN; Knight of the order of the GARTER, and Chancelor of the Univerſity of OXFORD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Preſent you here with a handful of fruits ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of your own Field, which I humbly deſire may be acceptable to you, as I am accountable to you; ſo I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour continually to pleaſe God and your ſelf: this auditory
<pb facs="tcp:33453:3"/>among whom you have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give me a place, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo many noble perſons do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, ſhall be an everlaſting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of your Charitable piety. My Lord, our ſouls bleſs you, and our bowels which are refreſhed with the ſhadow of your name, ſhall carry the acknowledgment thereof up to Heaven. In theſe dayes full of horror and confuſion, the foxes hav holes, and the birds of the air have neſts; but the ſon of God hath not, in regard of us, where he may rest his head, if you had not lodged him amongſt us: even ſo may you lodge with him in his higheſt habitation. But my Lord live here firſt many ages, and in the end live eternally.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:3"/>
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the Preface of my Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations on the Creed, I have prevented the moſt of thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations which might be made againſt that Treatiſe, or theſe that follow: I could over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm them with reaſons, who yet demand, for what ſerv theſe things that I have uttered, to ſalvation? Now concerning Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxal points, in which you may ſee ſo many Looking-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Gods wiſdom; points I ſay cleared by innumerable ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial lights; conduce they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:33453:4"/>to ſalvation: but theſe people who ſpeak ſo Magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, imagine that nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to ſalvation, but what they find in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon places: and as all their learning conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in that vulgar kind of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo they think all Divinity is locked up within ſuch bounds.</p>
            <p>I need not anſwer thoſe who complain, that all here is of too high a taſte, and that I give them nothing but ſalt or ſpices; but it is free for them to take hereof as much as will ſeaſon the ordinary food of their mindes: and yet the acrimony which they find there, proceeds from their tenderneſs, but in accuſtoming themſelves, they
<pb facs="tcp:33453:4"/>will finde there the reliſh, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brity and nutritive vertue of Manna.</p>
            <p>Many for want of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the very principle, meet with many rubs and ſtumbling ſtones in the plaineſt ways that may be: if I ſhould ſay that <hi>Enoch</hi> is the third of thoſe who went out of the world; none having gone before but <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Adam,</hi> this were impercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible to thoſe who cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the 5 chapter of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> but I do not undertake to teach the rudiments I preſuppoſe, them, and I beleeve I ſpeak to thoſe who underſtand them.</p>
            <p>There be ſome who wiſh I had been ſomwhat more large
<pb facs="tcp:33453:5"/>in theſe obſervations, but theſe men complain that they are conducted the ſhorter way; I could furniſh them with words enough, but is not this for their advantage, that they hav in few words the whole ſubſtance of a Subject within this brevity, which I have expreſly ſtudied for, they ſhall finde ſtill ſtuff of a large breadth, if they will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold it from one end to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>I have the approbation of divers men eminent for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, even of ſome to whom I am otherways unknown; one of theſe under the name of the Genius of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen the Engliſh tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:33453:5"/>of my Obſervations on the Creed honored me with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Latin Epiſtle, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging me to publiſh theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tractats, which I promiſed. I know well that the Elogies which he gave me are too high to belong to me, but doubtleſs in exalting me, he would afford me matter of humiliation. Whoſoever thou art, if ever theſe lines ſhall come into thy hands, and if thou wilt be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to caſt thine eyes upon them; I beſeech thee by theſe many brave vertues, the ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles whereof I finde ſhining in thy letters, and by that ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy &amp; communion of thoughts which God hath put in us; do
<pb facs="tcp:33453:6"/>not conceal thy name from me, it ſhall be precious, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous alſo ſhall thy counſels be to me. <hi>O quis daret te ut fratrem mihi!</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:6"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The NATURAL MAN, and HIS QUALITIES.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>DIvers ſorts of good men in the Worlds opinion, and but onely one indeed.</hi> p. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore God was pleaſed that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſhould outgo the Saints in many vertuous actions.</hi> p. 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A conſideration upon the two laſt ſinners immediately converted by Chriſt,</hi> viz. <hi>the Thief and St.</hi> Paul. p. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whence comes it to paſs, that all men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally beleeve that they muſt be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Works?</hi> p. 9.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>Touching the pretended merit of WORKS.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>That the cauſes of our ſalvation are in heaven, the marks of it on earth.</hi> p. 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore is it that our Lord, ſpeaking of works according to which he will judge men at the laſt day, mentioneth none but works of mercy?</hi> Mat. 25.3. p. 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God hath choſen Faith rather then any other Vertue to be the inſtrument of our Juſtification: The difference between a miraculous Faith and a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying.</hi> p. 14.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thoſe that now adaies ſeek to be juſtified by works are more inexcuſable then thoſe that had this pretence before the death of Chriſt.</hi> p. 16.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>Good WORKS the Effects of FAITH.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſtrange reaſons by which the Scripture inviteth us to good works, with the method that it teacheth to make us ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of graces.</hi> p. 17.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why the common people love rather to hear ſpeak of Charity then Faith; of the Law then the Goſpel.</hi> p. 20.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of Repentance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore is it never ſaid that God repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of any thing, ſaving that which concern'd men?</hi> p. 22.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore hath God commanded divers things contrary unto common Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> p. 24.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Queſtion touching</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:33453:8"/>
                  <hi>accepting the choice that God gave them.</hi> p. 26.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why is Superſtition in things indifferent, held ſo hainous?</hi> p. 27.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Touching the TABLES of the LAVV in general.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A comparing of the two miraculous Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings that are reported in the holy Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</hi> p. 29.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How long the Tables of the Law endured, and a Conſideration upon that matter.</hi> p. 30.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The reaſon why the Scipture ſhews which is the greateſt Commandment, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which is the leaſt.</hi> p. 32.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How one may judge of two diverſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, to know which is greater then the other.</hi> p. 33:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why by the Law it was pollution to touch the dead corps of a godly man that had been murdered, and nevertheleſs it was
<pb facs="tcp:33453:8"/>not pollution to touch the living Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</hi> p. 34.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Preface of the Decalogue, <hi>Hearken, Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Degrees amongſt Nations, in regard of the love or hate that God bare to them.</hi> p. 35.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore is</hi> Nathaneel <hi>called an</hi> Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, <hi>or child of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>rather then the child of</hi> Jacob, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.47. p. 36.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God never works a Miracle to witneſs or prove that which a man may know na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally. But why then did he cauſe ſo many miracles to intervene at the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Law, ſeeing it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally known to men?</hi> p. 38.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:9"/>
            <list>
               <head>The I. COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt have no other gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A conſideration of the times wherein A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſme and Superſtition have general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reigned.</hi> p. 41.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>By the Example of the Phariſees and Sadduces, is ſhewed, that God rather pardons the ſuperſtitious, then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane.</hi> p. 42.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The true Religion, the eaſieſt. The folly of the Pagans affecting plurality of Gods.</hi> p. 43.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A conſideration upon the worſhip of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> p. 44.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Touching a kinde of Idolatry very ſubtil and uſual.</hi> p. 45.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore is it, that a man that hath falſe gods, leaves them not ſo eaſily, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſaketh the true?</hi> p. 47.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:9"/>
            <list>
               <head>The II. COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Who is more wicked, he that adds to the Ordinances of God, or he that detracts from them?</hi> p. 49.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the nature of painting that repreſents the Hiſtory of the Bible.</hi> p. 51.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>None ever made any image of God, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept God himſelf.</hi> p. 52.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhy was it that God, who often appeared in a viſible ſhape, would not manifeſt himſelf after this manner when he publiſhed the Law?</hi> p. 53.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>If we had the true pourtrait and very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of our Saviour Chriſt, taken from his own body; what account ought we to make of it?</hi> p. 55.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33453:10"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>A notable difference betwixt one of the figures which repreſented Chriſt, and thoſe that repreſented the Angels. And a conſideration upon the matter.</hi> p. 56.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhence is it, that in the Apocalyps, Ieſus Chriſt (being man) is decypher'd only in parabolical Figures, rather then in the natural form of his own body?</hi> p. 57.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhat's the reaſon, that amongſt all the wonders that God hath wrought, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made an Image to ſpeak?</hi> p. 58.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Two ſorts of ſinners at which God mocks.</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The admirable proportion, that God holds in the deſpenſation of his judgments.</hi> p. 60.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of whom are deſcended thoſe Nations that go naked?</hi> p. 66.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The number of Generations named in the Promiſe.</hi> p. 67.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Strange Examples of divers Subjects, in which God hath manifeſted both his Mercy and Iuſtice.</hi> p. 69.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why did God ſometimes take ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb facs="tcp:33453:10"/>care of the Patriarchs and their children, even of theſe that were wicked, and at this day he makes no ſuch addreſſes as he did then to them?</hi> p. 71.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God ſpent but ſix daies in Creating the World, and empleyed ſeven to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the walls of</hi> Jerico? p. 73.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The II. COMNANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God pronounceth the ſame word twice to the ſame purpoſe, againſt idle oathes?</hi> p. 75.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Although in ſome things God hath diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his law, yet he hath never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with faith; alſo of the ſtability of Gods oathes.</hi> p. 79.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:11"/>
            <list>
               <head>The IV. COMMANDMENT. Remember the Sabbath day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God never wrought any miracle on the Sabbath day, before the coming of Chriſt.</hi> p. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seven Sabbath daies which Chriſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his miracles.</hi> p. 84.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In what things our Saviour is to be immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</hi> p. 86.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whence it is that in the Hiſtory of the New Teſtament, we do not read that ever the</hi> Sadduces <hi>appeared on the Sabbath day?</hi> p. 87.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why the Law uſeth ſuch an excellent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi> viz. <hi>God's Reſt, as a reaſon for the beaſts to reſt?</hi> p. 90.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why none of the dead have been raiſed on the Sabbath day?</hi> p. 92.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:11"/>
            <list>
               <head>The V. COMMANDMENT. Honour thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whence comes it as they ſay commonly, That Love and Affection uſeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend: Difference between Faith &amp; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: The words of</hi> Mal. 4.5. <hi>diſcuſſed.</hi> p. 97.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why the Law expreſſeth the Childrens du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Parents by the word</hi> Honour, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by the word</hi> Love. p. 99.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wherefore the Law commanded Children to fear thoſe that brought them into the world, namely, the Mother before the Father.</hi> p. 100.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:12"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Promiſe annexed to the fift Commandment.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Examples, of that proportion which is found ſometimes between good works, and the recompence which they receive in this life.</hi> p. 102.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why fifteen years were added to the life of</hi> Ezechias. p. 104.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The age of the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>when they paſſed out of the Wilderneſs into the Land of Promiſe.</hi> p. 107.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The meaſure and proportion of mans life from time to time, ſince the firſt ages.</hi> p. 109.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>None of the Kings of</hi> Juda <hi>exceeded the age of ſeventy years.</hi> p. 111.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Difference between the faithful of the Old Teſtament, and thoſe of the New, concerning their deſire of long life: another difference about the reckoning of the yeas of their life.</hi> p. 112.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33453:12"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Three cauſes, why men are loath to leave this life, repreſented in him who died firſt.</hi> p. 113.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A moral obſervation upon the daies of</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus <hi>raiſed from the dead.</hi> p. 114.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The VI. COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not kill.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God in his titles doeth rather call Himſelf our</hi> Buckler, <hi>then our</hi> Sword. p. 116.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Since</hi> Moſes <hi>there have been but three men, who received power to kill any miraculouſly; and the ſame who have miraculouſly inflicted death on the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, have alſo given life to the dead. Reaſons of the one and the other.</hi> p. 117.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The plot of the Prieſts in conſulting to put</hi> Lazarus <hi>to death,</hi> John 12.10. p. 119.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A queſtion: If the puniſhment of a
<pb facs="tcp:33453:13"/>criminal being interrupted by ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary accident intervening, after the execution is begun, is it juſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him, of the puniſhment to which he was condemmed.</hi> p. 120.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An alluſion in the Apoſtles words, who ordains that the Sun go not down upon our anger,</hi> Epheſ. 4.26. p. 122.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The VII. COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God though he approves not Poligamy nor unlawful divorces, which were free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the old Teſtament, yet never forbad them, but by the laſt of all the Prophets?</hi> p. 124.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhy men are more ſubject to be aſhamed in the Act of any ſin, rather then in that of pride; and why more in Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, then in any other ſin?</hi> p. 127.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33453:13"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>What may be inferred upon this, that the Holy Ghoſt deſcribing under divers ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes the ſpiritual beauty of the Church, makes no mention of painting?</hi> p. 128.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A moral obſervation upon</hi> Sampſon's <hi>looſing of his ſtrength and ſight, and how he recovered the one, but not the other.</hi> p. 129.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The VIII COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why Chriſt uſed the example of theeves to induce us to ſearch for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven.</hi> p. 132.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An obſervation upon this, that among Chriſt's Diſciples, there is but one no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for avarice, but all are taxed for ambition.</hi> p. 135.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To one man onely God by divine means did ſhew the way to become rich</hi> p. 136.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A conjecture upon the Jewiſh opinion, touching the juſt price of things ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible.</hi> p. 138.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33453:14"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Queſtion: if he that hath made reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the goods unjuſtly detained, as alſo of all the profits and intereſts, and recompenced all the loſſes, hath he ſufficiently diſcharged his conſcience?</hi> p. 140.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sacriledge the firſt crime committed in the Church of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>after they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into</hi> Canaan. <hi>And the firſt in the Chriſtian Church.</hi> p. 142.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The IX. COMMADMENT. Thou ſhalt not bear falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whether it be more injurious to call our neighbour fool, or knave? And why a man glorieth rather to be eſteemed good then wiſe?</hi> p. 144.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Oſervation upon this; That in the Scripture God is oftner angry with
<pb facs="tcp:33453:14"/>mans wickedneſs, then he uſeth to laugh at their folly.</hi> p. 146.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Is it lawful to divulge falſe news, if it may ſerve for the publick good?</hi> p. 148.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhy it is lawful ſometimes to make ſhew of evil, but never lawful to make ſhew of good.</hi> p. 149.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVe may know a wicked man; but it is imposſible to know a good man.</hi> p. 151.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>When the Scripture ſpeaks of any man in Hell, it never names the man; and when it doth name him, it never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the name of Hell; an obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon this matter.</hi> p. 152.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The X. COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not covet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A ſin committed by rule and order is
<pb facs="tcp:33453:15"/>more enormous, then that which is done in diſorder and confuſion.</hi> p. 55.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The diverſity of conflicts in man againſt himſelf.</hi> p. 156.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why ſome ſee more eaſily the defects of the memory, and of other faculties of the ſoul, then the defects of their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> p. 159.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The correſpondency that is between the two Tables of the Law.</hi> p. 161.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>There is love in God but not Faith and Hope.</hi> p. 162.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whether it is a greater defect, to want Faith or Charity?</hi> p. 163.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In all the Hiſtory of that time which was before the law, the love of God was never mentioned in expreſs termes, but onely the fear of God.</hi> p. 165.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33453:15"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of them who excuſe their faults on this: That God hath not given them more underſtanding and judgement.</hi> p. 168.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In the duties of man towards God, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfullneſs is more culpable then igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> p. 169.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whence comes it, that contrary to all other affections, this which man carries to himſelf, hath no bounds; and why this never faileth, nor is ſubject to diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> p. 171.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why the older we grow, the more we love our ſelves?</hi> p. 173.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhy we do not envy another mans good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> p. 175.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33453:16"/>
            <list>
               <head>Divers Duties of the Law. A Concluſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why</hi> Moſes <hi>who wrought ſo great and many miracles, never raiſed any from the dead?</hi> p. 167.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Law continued from</hi> Moſes, <hi>who had an impediment in his ſpeech, till</hi> John <hi>the ſon of</hi> Zachary, <hi>which</hi> Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary <hi>was ſpeechleſs,</hi> Luke 16.16. p 168.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Why God in ſpeaking to man, uſeth more words, then when he is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpeaking to the creatures which want underſtanding; and why he uſeth ſo many words and repetitions to effect mans converſation, ſeeing he can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him, with one word onely.</hi> p. 170.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhy the Scripture ſpeaking of Vertue and Vice, doth command or prohibit one oftner then another.</hi> p. 172.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33453:16"/>
            <head>THE NATURAL MAN, and HIS QUALITIES.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Divers ſorts of good men in the World's o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and but onely one indeed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any men are honeſt, Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fear of men, aw'd by the ſeveritie of the laws; Or for the good that may come to them of it: as hee that is right and ſquare that he may keep his dealings afoot: Or for reputation; as it may fall out, that the onely deſire of glory may carry a man to give all he has to the poor; yea, to expoſe his body to the flames, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. Or for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33453:17"/>apprehenſion of hell; For many would be out of meaſure wicked, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it not that this fear holds them in. Or for the joyes of heaven; as he that asked of our Saviour, what he ſhould do to have eternal life. Or to ſatisfie their own conſcience, that preſſeth and ſoliciteth them to ſome vertuous action. Or out of a meer deſire they have to vertue it ſelf; as there are generous diſpoſitions, that ſeem to go with no other ſpring.</p>
               <p>Now in very deed, of all theſe ſorts of good men, there is none that is truly ſo. This aſſertion generally taken, may ſeem to be very unjuſt: For one will haply grant, that hee who is not godly but out of fear, or ſome intereſt hee pretends either in this world or that to come, hath no reall goodneſſe, but that hee hath a ſervile or mercenary ſoul. But you'l think it ſtrange, to ſay that he that works not but out of conſcience, and the ſole love he hath to vertue, ſhould not be a good man! for what is it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33453:17"/>to be an honeſt man, if this be not? and what is further needfull to have this quality?</p>
               <p>It ſeems true, that our actions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a nobler principle then this, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſatisfie conſcience, and to love Vertue for its own ſake: Yet this is not enough to be a right honeſt man. Wee muſt then preſuppoſe, that to ſpeak properly, and according to the language of God, There is no good work, but that which is done in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and out of love of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Good, which is God himſelf. For is it beleevable, that God may approve of a work in which himſelf is no way conſidered? Or that hee may take him for good that neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or is ignorant of the chief Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and hath no affection to it? This granted, it is evident why the onely love of Conſcience, or of Vertue, makes not an honeſt man; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſcience nor Vertue are God: they are amiable by reaſon of him that is the higheſt Goodneſſe; but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33453:18"/>whoſoever loveth them without him, knoweth not ſo much as what good is: Such was the goodneſſe of many the Pagans, and even ſuch is the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of many now adays.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore God was pleaſ'd that the Heathen ſhould outgo the Saints in many ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous actions.</head>
               <p>It is certain that in the Heathen Hiſtories we have more examples of Heroick Vertues then what are read in the Bible it ſelf. Let's mention but ſome of them. Wee praiſe the continencie of <hi>Joſeph:</hi> but that of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> came not ſhort of it. We talk of the Midwives which refuſed to obey Pharaohs command, by which they were enjoyned to ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle the Hebrew male-children as ſoon as born: but among infidels there have been ſlaves that rather choſe to be wrack'd in pieces, then to let fall word that might have prejudiced their Maſters. We commend the faithful
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33453:18"/>amity that was between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan:</hi> But how many examples of Pagans, that would have died for their friends? Wee have in eſteem the zeal of <hi>Phineas,</hi> that puniſhed the Adultery of the Iſraelite with the Madianitiſh woman; but is this act comparable to the juſtice of that Prince, who had rather that one of his own eyes ſhould be put out, and another of his own ſon that had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that Adultery, then to baffle the Law that ordained to put out both the eyes of him that ſhould be found guilty of that filth. We ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the generoſity of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be called the Son of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter, and gave over the ſway he bore in the Court of <hi>Egypt:</hi> but how many Monarchs have volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily laid aſide their Diadems, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd the majeſtie of the Scepter, to reduce themſelves to the obſcurity of a private life? We celebrate the abſtinence of <hi>David,</hi> who refuſed to drink the water that ſome of his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33453:19"/>Worthies had fetch'd him with danger of their lives, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. But divers Generals of Armies mortally wounded, would not have the bloud of their wounds ſtanched, nor permit the drawing out of the dart where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were clean ſhot through, before in the firſt place they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken order for the ſafety of their Souldiers. Wee further commend <hi>David,</hi> who (beholding that the plague wherewith the people were ſmitten was occaſioned through him) offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to puniſhment, that hee might deliver his Common-wealth: But ſome Pagans have made away themſelves, rather then they would be engaged to fight againſt their Country, that had unjuſtly baniſhed and confiſcated them. We proclaim the kindneſſe of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that was the nouriſher of his Father: but they ſpeak of ſuch a Son, who to ſave his Father, caſt himſelf into the midſt of the fire. We admire divers other examples of Vertue which are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33453:19"/>in the Scripture; but the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then have ſhewed actions far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond.</p>
               <p>Yet hath there always been more goodneſs and more vertue (without compariſon) in the Saints then in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels. Divers of the Pagans actions have been greater, verily, and more vigorous; but they were not enliven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the true principle of vertue, which is faith in God, and had not his glory for their aim: So many crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſurpaſſe man in divers acts of foreſight, naturall affection, courage, temperance, fidelity, grati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude, and yet they have but the reſemblances of Vertues; neither can one ſay that there is in them any morall good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>But ſee here our queſtion: Whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vertuous actions the heathen have performed, proceeded from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which gave them the inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them. Now wherefore did he enable them to do ſuch notable acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet accepted not their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33453:20"/>for it is impoſſible to pleaſe him without faith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. And why would he that even their works (in the ſenſe I have named) ſhould outſtrip thoſe of the Saints? Hee would verily teach us, that works, even the very beſt, have not merit e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nough to bring us neer to him: For if many that have been tranſcendent in divers vertuous acts, notwithſtanding have not obtained grace; And on the contrary, many that have been infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in works, are counted amongſt the friends of God; followeth it not, that if we be pleaſing unto him, it is not becauſe of our works?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A conſideration upon the two laſt ſinners immediately converted by Christ, <hi>viz.</hi> the Thief and S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>One was converted by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour on the Croſſe; the other by him in heaven: one entred Paradiſe the ſame day that Chriſt entred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead: The other was rap'd up
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33453:20"/>thither before ever he died. One re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented not but at the laſt hour of his life, amidſt his very puniſhment; the other found not his heart till he was caſt down with affrightment, by voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and viſion from heaven. One and the other (<hi>viz.</hi> the thief and <hi>Saul,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Paul</hi>) were (eſpecially this laſt) far enough from having any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Chriſt, then when his grace ſurpriſed them. Many ſuppoſe in a carnall a man power whereby he contributes to his own converſion. but <hi>Sauls</hi> example witneſſeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; he was in the very heat of his madneſs, when he was called from above; was he in a poſture to turn himſelf to Chriſt, then when he went againſt Chriſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whence comes it to paſſe, that all men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally beleeve that they muſt be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Works?</head>
               <p>It is ſufficiently known, that this opinion is natural to every man. All
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33453:21"/>of us harbour this prejudice within us. Thence it comes to paſſe, that all Religions except the Chriſtian, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally teach it; the Pagan, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetan, the Jew, yea, and many that profeſſe Chriſtianity, agree all in this point, and ſing all the ſame ſong. But how comes this to be falſe and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, ſeeing it is dictated by Nature it ſelf? We muſt remember, that by the law of the Creation, it is ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that man ſhould be juſtified by his works, and that by them he ſhould live for ever. This principle was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved in the minde of man, who ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily had had righteouſneſs and life by his works, had he ſtood in his primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive innocencie; but his fall hath bruiſed his bones, making him unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of accompliſhing this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But he yet retains this ancient principle which hath been left him, to the end he ſhould remember whence he is fallen; not to make him beleeve that he can do that now, which he could in the ſtate of innocencie.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33453:21"/>
            <head>Touching the pretended merit of WORKS.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>That the Cauſes of our ſalvation are in heaven, the Marks of it on earth.</head>
               <p>IN the ſearch of theſe two points, we muſt take two contrary ways. For the Book of life wherein we are enrolled to ſalvation, and the mercy of God which calls us to it, and his grace that diſpenſeth it, and the Saviour that hath purchaſed it, muſt be ſought in heaven. On the other ſide; as we have on earth the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſalvation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Goſpel, the Sacraments, Faith; ſo likewiſe the ſame faith, the teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt, the peace of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and our works themſelves are here on earth the marks of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Divers overturn this method;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33453:22"/>ſuppoſing to be ſaved by vertue of their works: and on the other ſide, teaching that none can be ſaved if he be not one of Gods cloſet: In the one, they place on earth the Cauſes of our ſalvation; in the other, they ſeek the Marks of it in heaven; and in both the two they are as wide of the mark, as heaven is from earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore is it that our Lord, ſpeaking of works according to which he will judge men at the laſt day, mentioneth none but works of mercy? <hi>Matth. 25.35.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This paſſage preſents unto us the ſentence that ſhall be given upon men at that great day: where it ſpeaks of nothing ſave feeding thoſe that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred, receiving ſtrangers, clothing the naked, viſiting the ſick and thoſe in priſon: And on the contrary, of not having performed ſuch deeds of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence. But are there no works but theſe worthy to be remembred before Chriſts Tribunall, and that are able
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33453:22"/>to declare us juſt? or are there no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins except the omiſſion of ſuch duties? no other crime that deſerves damnation? Yes, there are works that excell theſe: he that ſpends his bloud and life for Chriſts ſake, doth a deed far ſurpaſſing him that gives clothes and food to the poor; to be a priſoner for the Goſpel, is more then to viſit priſoners. How is it then that this ſentence expreſſeth naught ſave the works of mercy, although that there be many other kindes of works?</p>
               <p>Let us conſider, That at the day of judgement all will certainly crave mercy. When all the kindreds of the earth ſhall lament before this Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Judge, what ſhall we hear men call for but mercy? As then all men will crave that mercy may be ſhew'd them, God will judge them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the mercy they have ſhown or neglected: Judgment that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked themſelves ſhall be forced to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove; For it is juſt that he ſhould be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33453:23"/>denyed mercy that would uſe no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>James</hi> 2.13. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reckoning up the charitable offices <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> had done him in priſon, wiſheth that he may finde mercy in that day, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. that is to ſay, he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mercy toward me, the Lord ſhew it to him: whereupon it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, againſt the opinion of merit, that even our mercy hath need of mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God hath choſen Faith rather then any other Vertue to be the inſtrument of our Juſtification: The difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a miraculous Faith and a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying.</head>
               <p>There is no Vertue whereof man taketh not occaſion to vant himſelf, except Faith: Man oftentimes boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of his Charity, Patience, Juſtice, yea, which is ridiculous, many wax proud of their Humility. But as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtifying Faith, none can brag of that: Why? This Fath hath for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33453:23"/>its object the mercy of God, which preſuppoſeth mans miſery; and his miſery lies in that hee is culpable; whereof it is impoſſible that he ſhould ever vant himſelf: On the contrary, this Faith overthrows the pride of man.</p>
               <p>There is indeed a ſort of Faith, from which men oftentimes have drawn matter of oſtentation; that is the faith of Miracles, as they call it. Divers have turn'd the gift of tongues to vanity; as likewiſe the other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous effects which God wrought by their hands, as is evident by the Apoſtles diſcourſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. We muſt mark here, That the faith of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles hath for its formall object, the power of God, which ſometimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes man to be either the ſubject or inſtrument of his Marvels. Now it may eaſily come to paſſe, that man may abuſe this honour: But he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deal ſo by juſtifying Faith, whoſe object is Gods mercy, which excludes all mans vanting, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33453:24"/>
               <head>Thoſe that now adayes ſeek to be juſtified by works, are more inexcuſable then thoſe that had this pretence before the death of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>Although the doctrine that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains that a ſinner is juſtified by his works, hath ever been vain and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; yet is it become more odious ſince the bloud of Chriſt (on which our juſtification is grounded) was ſhed for our ſins. For as long as yet there was no payment made for the ſin of men, it was not ſo ſtrange that many endeavored to give ſatisfaction therein, every man for himſelf: But after that Chriſt hath made actuall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction therein, we cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to pay without accuſing him of inſufficiency, and charge our ſelves with an ingratitude more hainous then that of the old Phariſaiſme.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33453:24"/>
            <head>Good WORKS the Effects of FAITH.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The ſtrange reaſons by which the Scripture inviteth us to good works, with the method that it teacheth to make us ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of graces.</head>
               <p>THe Vulgar think they are in the right, whenas in ſtead of myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Faith, they cry out, that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ought to ſpeak to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, preach good works, and controll vice. Theſe people by prejudice, that proceeds from common igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, make void the firſt and chiefeſt part of Chriſtianity, and maintain many capitall errours. An errour to imagine, that good life conſiſts not but in works; as if to well living were not requiſite right beleeving. An er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to ſay, that the hearing the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33453:25"/>points of Religion which are meerly ſpeculative, is of no force at all to make a man better. So much ſay the Jews, when they ſpeak of the Goſpel; for they demand to what purpoſe 'tis to be a good man to know that Jeſus Chriſt hath ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> that he was crucified, dead and buried? An errour to think that the conſcience hath not need of matters that are directed onely to the underſtanding, as well as of thoſe that onely concern the affections: as if a man ſhould not have need of his eys as well as his hands. An errour, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that Vertues muſt be taught onely by their proper deſcriptions and expreſſe precepts, after the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Moraliſts; for that is to plant the tree by tops of the boughs, in ſtead of planting it by the root.</p>
               <p>Let us hence conſider the motives which God himſelf maketh uſe of, when he preacheth us good works. The Scripture inviteth us to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Vertues, and hate of ſins;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33453:25"/>Foraſmuch (ſaith it) as ye have been baptized into the death of Chriſt, and buried with him: foraſmuch as hee that is our paſſover is offered up: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Chriſt is raiſed; foraſmuch as death hath no more dominion over him, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. What kind of arguments are theſe to induce us to good works? he invites us to them by the Articles of our faith, by matters very wide from the ſubject. There is more yet: For he ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to the doing them by reaſons which even ſeem to perſwade the clean contrary. Is this a reaſon that may put a man in fear to turn him from ſin, when one tels him that he is not under the law but under grace, and that God hath ordained to ſave him? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.8, 9. This believing, ſeems it not more fit (as ſome falſly have thought) to bring in Libertiniſme then the fear of ſin?</p>
               <p>But we muſt conſider that which is ſeen even in Nature it ſelf, the root and the fruit for the moſt part are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33453:26"/>not alike, neither in ſhape, colour nor taſte; yea, many times the fruit comes of a root altogether contrary in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Let Ignorance judge of it as it will, let the myſteries by which Faith is planted and watered ſeem to them unprofitable. This Faith is the root of graces; through it our works are purified, and without it it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to bring forth good fruit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why the common people love rather to hear ſpeak of Charity then Faith; of the Law then the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>It is well enough known, that the common people are more ſatisfied with an Exhortation, or a Diſcourſe upon Alms, or brotherly friendſhip, or Temperance, or ſome other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, then with any rare obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on a Point of the Goſpel. Now ſee the reaſon of it. The things of the Law are naturally written in our hearts, at leaſt in part; ſo that they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33453:26"/>are familiar, and intelligible to us, as domeſtick: Beſides, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to naturall Reaſon, which is the nobleſt faculty of man. But the matters of Faith, which Nature knows not, and which come from far, and which are tranſmitted by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way then that of humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are ſtrangers to our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; ſo that they are not received with ſo much welcome.</p>
               <p>Thence it comes to paſſe, that ſo many ſouls are found out of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, when one ſpeaks to them of ſome myſtery on which they never thought. The Law (truly) and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Tenents ought to be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but it is a brutiſh ingratitude, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that pretence, to refuſe to learn the ſecrets whereof the goodneſſe of God vouchſafeth to make us an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture. I will not here ſtand to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the common ſaying, which I have elſewhere obſerved, amongſt thoſe of the Vulgars, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Doctrine of Works is the principall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33453:27"/>in Religion. They that ſay ſo, know not the importance of what they ſay. For the Doctrine of the Mercy of God, of the Redemption accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by Jeſus Chriſt, and of his other ſaving Works, is that leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable then that which treats of mens works, or is the Law more then the Goſpel?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Repentance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore is it never ſaid that God repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him of any thing, ſaving that which concern'd men?</head>
               <p>ACcording to the Scripture terms, which wee ought to take in a ſenſe that derogateth not from the Divine Wiſdome, we finde, among divers paſſages which touch this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, three things whereof God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33453:27"/>Firſt, That hee had made man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6. Secondly, That he had choſe <hi>Saul</hi> King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That he had pronounced the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of <hi>Ninive, Jonah</hi> 3.10. But why is it never ſaid, That God repented that he had made the Angels which became Divels? Hath he not as much cauſe to be ſorry that he gave them being? Or why likewiſe did he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver repent that he had made the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which ſerved for an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the impoſture of that wicked Spirit?</p>
               <p>The Scripture never attributes any repentance to God, but when he is to deal about man. The reaſon of it is, that by this expreſſion he might bring man to repentance. Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (to ſpeak properly) is not at all in God; but God attributes it to himſelf, to ſhew that it ought to be in man. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 18.8. <hi>If the Nation againſt whom I ſhall have ſpoken, turn from the evill it hath committed, I will alſo repent me of the evill that I thought to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33453:28"/>do unto it.</hi> Amongſt the creatures, onely man is capable of Repentance; that's the reaſon it is never ſaid, God repents, except when there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what about man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore hath God commanded divers things contrary unto common Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</head>
               <p>We finde, that God hath given commandments contrary to clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, contrary to ſhamefac'dneſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to humanitie, contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to all appearance, and common ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Againſt cleanneſſe, he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to ſeeth his bread with mans excrements, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.12. Againſt ſhame, he ordained circumciſion, and honoured it with the name of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Againſt humanity, he would have all the young children in <hi>Jeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> maſſacred. Againſt nature, hee gave order to <hi>Abraham</hi> to turn out of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33453:28"/>doors his ſon <hi>Iſhmael.</hi> Againſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of a cauſe, he made an Ark to be built, therein to ſhut <hi>Noah</hi> and the creatures, which with more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood he might have lodg'd upon ſome mountain. Againſt common ſenſe, a Prophet following the word of the Lord, ſaid unto another man, Smite mee: This man refuſing to ſmite him, is condemned to be ſlain by a Lion, and that for not obeying the word of the Lord, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.35, 36. a ſtrange command, and which ſeemed rather to come from the mouth of a mad man, then from the wiſdom of God.</p>
               <p>But why hath God commanded things that ſeem ſo abſurd? To let us underſtand, that there is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple more high and more noble then our common reaſon, then ordinary decency, then humanity, then nature it ſelf. All that we call juſt, beſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, humane, reaſonable, bears not this name but in reſpect of God, which hath given it to it, and hath there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33453:29"/>imprinted his mark: And when it pleaſeth him, he can give the ſame titles, and in effect the ſame quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to actions that have a name quite contrary. Then that which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, ſhamefull, ridiculous, cruel, and unreaſonable, becomes holy, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, full of reaſon and juſtice. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, by ſuch commands, God hath been pleaſed to ſhew, that he would be obeyed, not ſo much for the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ſplendor of the action, as for the authority of him that enjoyned it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Queſtion touching <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> accepting the choice that God gave them.</head>
               <p>To the one God gave leave to chuſe ſuch a judgement as he liked, out of the three that he propounded him: To the other hee gave the choice of ſuch a favour as he would ask. Both accepted of the offer. One choſe the Peſtilence, the other made
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33453:29"/>his choice of Wiſdom. But it ſeems, they had done better to have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the choice to God himſelf onely out of reſpect, and to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to ſend them what hee thought fitteſt for them: So one would have thought. But it is not permitted us to diſobey out of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie. If God commands mee to chuſe, he will that I look to it that I chuſe well. Wherefore then ſhall I fruſtrate his intention, in deluding his Ordinance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why is Superſtition in things indifferent, held ſo hainous?</head>
               <p>He that out of conſcience abſtains from that which is not forbidden, or enthrals himſelf to that which is left unto his liberty, ſeems not to offend but through obedience; is this then ſo great a crime?</p>
               <p>I let alone the wrong this Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition doth to God; but otherwiſe it ſins againſt nature. There are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33453:30"/>to which God hath made man ſubject; there are alſo actions that God hath made ſubject to man: thoſe we call Neceſſary, theſe Indifferent. Now when man makes his conſcience ſubject unto thoſe very things that are ſubject unto him, by ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order he degrades himſelf, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons the rank in the which God and Nature hath placed him. How are they to blame then, that teach the making ſcruple almoſt of every thing? that put thorns every where? that frighten conſciences with apparitions and vain ſcarcrows? that fetter and load them with a thouſand unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table burthens.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33453:30"/>
            <head>Touching the TABLES of the LAW in generall.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A comparing of the two miraculous Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings that are reported in the holy Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie.</head>
               <p>THeſe two Writings that were made without the hand of man, are, firſt that which God form'd upon the Tables of ſtone, containing the Decalogue. Afterward, that which he drew upon the wall of the Hall of <hi>Baltſhazzar,</hi> expreſſing the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ruine of that Monarchie, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. The one was made preſently after the People of Iſraels going forth out of the Egyptian bondage: the other, upon the time that they were to go forth of the Babyloniſh Captivity. It is notable, that the Babylonians had cauſed the firſt Writing to be loſt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33453:31"/>then when the Temple was burnt, where were the Tables of the Law kept in the Ark. But for that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they lifted up themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Authour of this Writing, God made them ſee another, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the decree of their ruine, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.23, 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How long the Tables of the Law endured, and a Conſideration upon that matter.</head>
               <p>I ask not what is become of that precious Writing, whoſe characters were the handy work of God. Theſe Tables were never ſeen after the burning of the firſt Temple, in the which it is believed that they periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well as the Ark in which they were incloſed.</p>
               <p>Now, from the time that they were given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> untill that time they ceaſed (that is to ſay, the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Temple) paſs'd nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeers, and ſomething above: Certain Chronologers reckon therein
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33453:31"/>nine hundred and ſix: others, nine hundred and fifteen: others, nine hundred twenty ſeven: others go to nine hundred and thirty. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we may note, that according to the exacteſt ſupputations, the durance of the Tables of the Law paſt not the number of <hi>Adams</hi> yeers, who having firſt received the Law written in the tables of his heart, lived the age of nine hundred and thirty yeers. At the leaſt it is certain, and ſeems very worthy of note, That neither the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Tables of the Law, nor the life of any man have never attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the age of a thouſand yeers. The Law ſaid, Whoſoever fulfilled it, ſhould live for ever: but for want of fulfilling it, the life of man never reach'd a thouſand yeers. And God in like manner would not that the Tables wherein he had renewed this Law that offered life, ſhould laſt a thouſand yeers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33453:32"/>
               <head>The reaſon why the Scripture ſhews which is the greateſt Commandement, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which is the leaſt.</head>
               <p>Although there be a difference of degrees &amp; weight between the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; and that the Law-giver hath mark'd that which is the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, yea and the ſecond likewiſe, to which all the other are referred; yet would hee never ſay which was the leaſt of them all, in the one or other Table. His will is, (notwithſtanding the inequality which is betwixt them) that we conſider them all as great, ſeeing that in the Law there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is not great in effect. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is neceſſary to know which is the greateſt Commandement in each of the two Tables, becauſe all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are (as it were) inchaff'd into the greater: But to know which is the leaſt, is in no wiſe neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33453:32"/>
               <head>How one may judge of two diverſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, to know which is greater then the other.</head>
               <p>Thoſe that concern God, and touch him neareſt, or that render man moſt like God, thoſe are the greateſt. Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (for example) is that Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which immediately reſpects the ſervice of God, then that which hath other ends, although ſubordinate: So <hi>Mary</hi> had choſen the better part. Greater is the ſpirituall ſervice of God then the externall; becauſe it hath more correſpondence with God, who is a Spirit. Charity is greater then Faith or Hope; becauſe Love is in God, yea God himſelf is Love; but neither Faith nor Hope can be in him: For what ſhould God either beleeve or hope for? Greater is his work that ſaves a mans life, then his that buries him dead; becauſe the living bears the image of God. Upon this laſt example
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33453:33"/>I will make a Digreſſion, yet not far from the matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why by the Law it was pollution to touch the dead corps of a godly man that had been murdered, and nevertheleſſe it was not pollution to touch the living Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</head>
               <p>We know, that whoſoever touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a dead body (even for to bury it) the Law declared him defiled. So a godly man being ſlain, all that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him after his death, fell into this ceremoniall irregularity. But if they touched the murtherer, though his hands as yet all gored in his bloud, they endangered no uncleanneſſe. This Law is ſtrange, and it ſeems hard to finde a reaſon of it. We may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer notwithſtanding, That as there were divers cauſes of pollution, that of a dead mans body proceeded from that he had loſt the image of God, the lineaments of which conſiſt properly in the ſoul. Now a living man, though
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33453:33"/>a murtherer, carries notwithſtanding, in regard of the ſubſtance of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul, this image, which the dead man hath no longer.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Preface of the Decalogue. <hi>Hearken, Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Degrees amongſt Nations, in regard of the love or hate that God bare to them.</head>
               <p>TWo Nations have of old been famous for two contrary reaſons. One, as being the moſt beloved of God, to wit, <hi>Iſrael:</hi> the other, the moſt hated, <hi>viz. Amalek.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongſt the people that God held in hatred, the Idumean and Egyptian were leſſe hated then the Moabite and Ammonite, and theſe leſſe then the Amalekite. The Idumean and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian were excluded the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33453:34"/>of the Lord to the third gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: the Moabite and Ammonite entered not in thither till the tenth: the Amalekite was not onely ſhut out thence for ever, but alſo condemned to be totally rooted out from under heaven. 'Tis that onely Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom God hath denounced immortall War; that alone that ever he commanded wholly to ſuppreſſe. The cauſes of the difference that God put between theſe infidel people, are touched in <hi>Deuteronomie, chap.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 25. <hi>v.</hi> 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore is <hi>Nathaneel</hi> called an <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,</hi> or childe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> rather then the childe of <hi>Jacob, Joh. 1.47.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'Tis known, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> was but the ſame man, and that his Poſterity are ſometimes called the children of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſometime of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Not that it is indifferent to call them by the one or the other name. For there be reaſons and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33453:34"/>for which they ought to be called rather by the one then the other name. But paſſing over what the Learned have heretofore obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therupon, I have one obſervation to produce hence.</p>
               <p>The high Prophet ſpeaking of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaneel,</hi> ſaith, that hee was verily an Iſraelite in whom there was no guile. This man then is praiſed as ſincere, and that knew not what it was to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent any man: In this quality he was none of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s childe, that had ſupplanted his brother, ſtealing away his bleſſing by a falſe ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Jacob</hi> had ſometime been frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent; but <hi>Iſrael</hi> was always ſound. For being as yet but <hi>Jacob,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives both brother and father too: but after he was honoured with the name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his actions were ever without deceit. On good reaſon then the name of <hi>Iſraelite</hi> is rather given to <hi>Nathaneel,</hi> then the name of a childe of <hi>Jacob.</hi> And here, as through the whole Scripture is ſeen the admirable
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33453:35"/>ſtile of the Divine Wiſdom, to whom only it belongs to appropriate names unto their true natures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>God never works a Miracle to witneſſe or prove that which a man may know na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally. But why then did he cauſe ſo many Miracles to intervene at the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Law, ſeeing it is naturla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to men?</head>
               <p>God doth nothing ſuperfluous: that's the reaſon he never raiſed up Prophet, or ſent Angel to foretell Eclipſes, or other events that may be foreſeen by ordinary wayes. Was it neceſſary then that God ſhould come down from heaven to earth, with ſuch a miraculous demonſtration of his glory, to come tell men, that they muſt honour Father and Mother? to give them to underſtand that they muſt not kill, nor bear falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
               <p>I forbear to ſay, that this Law that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33453:35"/>was publiſhed in <hi>Sinai,</hi> contains points which a man cannot underſtand but by ſupernaturall revelation; for we had never known how many dayes God beſtowed in creating the whole Univerſe, if himſelf had not reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this ſecret, which he expreſſeth in the fourth Commandment of the Decalogue: Yea moreover, what the Law carries in its very frontiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, <hi>(I am the Lord thy God)</hi> could not be known by any naturall means.</p>
               <p>To clear this, we muſt again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that God never names him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the God of thoſe he hates. The revelation comprehended in theſe words <hi>(I am thy God)</hi> is an expreſſion of benevolence and graciouſneſſe: Now this his ſaving benevolence could not be known by any voyce of Nature. We ſay further, that here are two points to be diſtinguiſhed: one, that there is a God; the other, that he is our God. The firſt, that there is a God, is written naturally
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33453:36"/>in our hearts: which is the reaſon that never yet Angel deſcended from heaven to come and tell men that there is a God. But to make them know that God is their God, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them of his loving-kindneſſe, to bring them injunctions from him; and in brief, to atteſt and confirm that which they could not learn from any naturall principle, God hath wrought miracles, hath cauſed Angels to ſpeak, yea hath ſpoke himſelf.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="commandment">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33453:36"/>
            <head>The I. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other gods,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A conſideration of the times wherein A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme and Superſtition have generally reigned.</head>
               <p>TWo crimes are forbidden in this firſt Commandment of the Law: One, not to have a God; the other, to have more then one. Theſe two ſins are very ancient in the world: yet it ſeems that Atheiſme was the firſt, or at leaſt Profaneneſs, which comes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neer to Atheiſme. We read not, that before the Flood there was any Idolatry amongſt men: The holy Hiſtory (<hi>Gen.</hi> 6.) marking out the cauſe of their deſtruction, ſeems ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to accuſe them for having had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33453:37"/>no God at all, then for having had many. After the Flood, though A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme was on foot ſtill in the world, yet was Idolatry far more generall. But as the corruption of mankinde began by Atheiſme or Profaneneſs, it makes as though it would return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again. The firſt Ages have been Atheiſts, the following ages Idolaters, and the laſt, into which we are fallen, is already wholly diſpoſed unto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme. And when the Son of man comes, he ſhall not finde faith upon the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>By the example of the Phariſees and Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, is ſhewed, that God rather par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons the Superſtitious, then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane.</head>
               <p>The Phariſee was ſuperſtitious, but the Sadduce inclined to Atheiſm, ſeeing that he beleeved not the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoul, neither the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body, nor the life to come. Now we finde, that divers
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33453:37"/>Phariſees (notwithſtanding the envie and ill will with which they were fore-ſtalled) became capable of the Faith, and received the Goſpel. One of the moſt eminent of this Sect, <hi>viz. Nicodemus,</hi> ſpent both his coſt and his pains in the buriall of Chriſt. But never read wee of any Sadduce that was converted to Chriſtianity. Not that God hath been wanting either in goodneſs or power to their converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but (as it ſeems) he would have it ſeen, that (in diſdaining to make them his Diſciples) he more deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the profane, then the ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Such a Phariſee that had even perſecuted the Church, was promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as high as unto an Apoſtleſhip: But never any Sadduce came ſo much as to the quality of a Diſciple.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The true Religion, the eaſieſt. The folly of the Pagans affecting plurality of gods.</head>
               <p>Falſe Religions have a thouſand
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33453:38"/>objects, a thouſand troubleſome win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and every of them trails the minde of man now into one danger, by and by into another. But true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath but one God, one Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, one Sacrifice expiatorie, one ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying Faith, one Baptiſme, one myſticall Body, and one onely Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. How much the more we multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this Union, ſo much the leſſe have we of Religion.</p>
               <p>But the poor Pagans took it clean contrary; for they that had the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number of gods, counted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt religious. It was the wiſdom of the Greeks and Romans to ſeek all the gods they heard tell of, yea all they could imagine; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that to have many gods, was to have much Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A conſideration upon the Worſhip of Angels.</head>
               <p>The moſt ſpecious and fair ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idolatry was the adoration of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33453:38"/>creatures ſo noble, and ſo far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove us. Theſe celeſtiall ſpirits have ſometimes come and ſpoke to men; but their communication was ever ſhort; they did, as it were, but paſſe by, without ever permitting any to know them. Now it ſeems, that the Wiſdom of God would that every of their apparitions ſhould be but of ſmall continuance, not to give time to the curioſity and feebleneſs of man, that inclines to Superſtition, to ask them queſtions from the matter, or to idolatrize their preſence. Of all mortall men that the Angels have longeſt held in diſcourſe at one time, Saint <hi>John</hi> the Divine was He; who ſuffered himſelf to be carried away with an exceſſe of ſubmiſſion toward them, <hi>Apocalyps</hi> 19.22. And ſince that time, Angels have forborn to ſpeak and commune with men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Touching a kinde of Idolatry very ſubtill and uſuall.</head>
               <p>Many common people ſay, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33453:39"/>they put their confidence in the true Religion, in their prayers, and in the juſtice of their cauſe, which is the ſame with Gods own. It will ſeem to them very ſtrange, if one tell them that they deceive themſelves; and that one muſt truſt neither in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, although true; nor in any of its duties; neither in our juſt right, though God himſelf be concern'd in it.</p>
               <p>But they ought to conſider, that we cannot nor ought not to put our confidence but in God alone. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not God: Religion is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that one renders to God, but it is not God. Even the very Ark of God that held the Tables of the Law, is called the might of God, and his glory; and yet it ſufficeth, that it was taken, and carried about in triumph by his enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.61. Our faith is not reſted upon a quality that God giveth unto a Cauſe, nor in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that he takes in it; but it is faſtened and ſtayed on God himſelf, who is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33453:39"/>its proper object. This diſtinction, that many will judge unprofitable, and of little ſolidity, is notwithſtanding neceſſary: and for want of taking heed to it, we fall into an imperceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Idolatry, and which is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore is it, that a man that hath falſe gods, leaves them not ſo eaſily, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſaketh the true?</head>
               <p>The Iſraelites were ſometimes leſs conſtant in the ſervice of the true God, then the Pagans in the worſhip of their Idols. This is caſt in their their teeth, <hi>Jerem. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Go thorow the Iſles of Kittim, and behold,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is there any Nation that hath changed their gods, which notwithſtanding are not gods? But my people hath changed their glory into that which is nothing worth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is natural, and an effect of the weakneſſe of humane judgment. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men deſire to have a god that may have ſome proportion with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33453:40"/>themſelves, and who may not be too far above the reach of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: Thence it comes, that if a man will make choice of a deity, he will rather chuſe any God then the true. The true God is infinitely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above us; and between his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ours there is an immeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſtance. But all other Deity that a man can imagine to himſelf, is found fitted unto mans capacity, and within ſome kenning; which is the reaſon that he the more eaſily faſteneth upon it, more willingly ſets up his reſt there, and more hardly forgoes it. And on the other ſide, it is more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for him to adhere to a God that is ſo far both from our ſenſes and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="commandment">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33453:40"/>
            <head>The .II. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Who is more wicked, he that adds to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, or he that detracts from them?</head>
               <p>ALl the corruptions that happen in Religion come by one of theſe wayes; <hi>viz.</hi> either of addition, or ſubſtraction: Both are noted and cenſured within the percloſe of the Bible, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.18, 19. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſeems that one is more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and abominable then the other: One leads to Superſtition, the other to Atheiſme. Hee that adds to the rules God hath preſcribed, becomes ſuperſtitious; and hee that takes thence, becoms a Libertine. One loads
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33453:41"/>himſelf with ſuperfluous burdens; the other ſhakes off the neceſſary yoak that God had impoſed upon him. Now if a man takes away once one point of Religion, and takes away yet another, and continues always taking away, at the end no Religion is left him: So that we ſee that theſe cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings off and diminutions end at length in Atheiſme, which is far worſe then Superſtition.</p>
               <p>Theſe two Sects, ſo famous in the Hiſtory of the New Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> Phariſaiſme and Saddueeiſme, lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe two extremities: The Phariſee ſewed his Traditions to the Scripture, and annexed to it an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of ordinances. The Sadduce ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt a main part of the Scripture, yea all the Prophets except <hi>Moſes:</hi> he annull'd the Reſurrection of the dead, denyed the being of Angels and all Spirits, and in divers manners man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled the Religion, turning it almoſt into Atheiſme.</p>
               <p>Sometime it falls out that the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33453:41"/>Scripture is gelded in favour of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> takes out of the Decalogue this ſecond Commandment, or confounds it with the firſt, or withdraws it from the eys and ears of the people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the nature of painting that repreſents the Hiſtorie of the Bible.</head>
               <p>There are many things are more clearly ſet forth in a picture then in a diſcourſe. The fabrick of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, the architecture of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the dimenſions, ſtories, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers rooms of <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, are more perceptible by us in a painting to the eye, then is the verbal deſcription the Scripture gives us of it. A man ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily may behold the ſituation and length of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> better in a Chorographick Map, then in the Hiſtory of <hi>Joſuah:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that which is the more evident and eaſie, is not nevertheleſſe the more excellent. Theſe paintings are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33453:42"/>not divine, as are the words of the Scripture. A viſible repreſentation of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple is meerly a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane figure; but the verball repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the ſame Temple exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in Scripture terms is a divine work. The picture of a man crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is it as divine as the words of the Scripture deſcribing the paſſion of Chriſt? or rather, is it comparable to a Sermon, in which Jeſus Chriſt is drawn out before our eyes, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified among us? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. Where is it authorized by God to plant Faith in our hearts? In many narrations a picture verily may ſerve for an help to the underſtanding of the Hiſtorie: but it can never be either inſtrument or object of our Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>None ever made any image of God, except God himſelf.</head>
               <p>There is none but God can make the image of God: Only man, among all the viſible creatures, is this Image:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33453:42"/>but hee cannot ſhape it in another matter; no, not in another man. A Father doth not ſo much as propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate it to his children: for though they alſo bear this image, yet they receive it not from him, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly from God, who alone imprints in them his reſemblance. The Scripture marks out this diſtinction, where it ſaith, that God made man after the likeneſſe of God: but that <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>Seth</hi> after his own likeneſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.1, 3. Man bringeth forth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after the image of man; but God onely faſhions them to the image of God. So the Soul, in which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly conſiſts the lines and lineaments of this divine Image, is not the work of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why was it that God, who often appeared in a viſible ſhape, would not manifeſt himſelf after this manner when he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the Law?</head>
               <p>He cauſed himſelf to be ſeen by the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33453:43"/>Ancients of Iſrael, and under his feet there was (as it were) a paved work of Saphir ſtone, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.10. He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto <hi>Daniel</hi> in the ſhape of an old man, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. He manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf yet other times in a viſible ſhape. But when hee came down to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Law, although he gave many illuſtrious tokens of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yet would he not appear in the figure of man, or do any other thing which might ſeem to repreſent him. Why not then, as well as in his other occurrences?</p>
               <p>The Wiſdome of God held it not fit to manifeſt himſelf under any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance then, when he forbad to make any reſemblance of himſelf: For ſeeing he never permitted his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation (no not in the ſhapes like to thoſe he had appeared under) it was not to the purpoſe to let one be ſeen then, when he forbade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be repreſented under any. If he had appeared in any viſible form, one might have thought, that it was
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33453:43"/>lawfull to repreſent him, at leaſt in the ſhape he ſhewed himſelf in then, ſeeing that it was at the publiſhing of the Law, which was given to learn men what they ſhould do. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tels us why in this action he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore to be ſeen after the ſort that he had manifeſted himſelf in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations; <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.11, 15, 16. <hi>Ye heard a Voice ſpeaking, but ye ſaw not any like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. Yee have not ſeen any likeneſſe in the day that the Lord ſpake unto thee in Horeb out of the middle of the fire; for fear thou ſhouldeſt corrupt thy ſelf, and ſhouldſt make thee any carved image or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, which may repreſent any thing unto thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>If wee had the true pourtrait and very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of our Saviour Chriſt, taken from his own body; what account ought we to make of it?</head>
               <p>Had I ſuch a picture, I would keep it as moſt precious, not onely above
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33453:44"/>all other painting; but as one of the moſt worthy objects of mans ſight: But I would ever make more account of the leaſt Chriſtian then of ſuch a Picture: For a Chriſtian repreſents Chriſt a great deal better then any paint. A true humane body anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not onely with a reaſonable ſoul, but alſo with the ſpirit of Chriſt, doth it not more reſemble Chriſt then a dead Crucifix, or a ſhape that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth nothing but ſome ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lineaments? I ſay more; That if one would abuſe this Picture, and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrize it, I would do by it as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did by the brazen Serpent, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A notable difference betwixt one of the figures which repreſented Chriſt, and thoſe that repreſented the Angels. And a conſideration upon the matter.</head>
               <p>In the Old Teſtament Chriſt was figured by the image of a Serpent ſet upon a pole, without the Tabernacle,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33453:44"/>in an open place: But the Angels were figured by the faces of men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wings, placed over the Ark it ſelf, in the moſt holy of Holies. If we conſider theſe figures, and their placing, that of Chriſts was greatly inferiour unto that of the Angels: And if the true image of Chriſt did conſiſt in outward lineaments, an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſhape had been fitter there then that of a Serpent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whence is it, that in the Apocalyps, Jeſus Christ (being man) is decyphered one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in parabolicall Figures, rather then in the naturall form of his own body?</head>
               <p>We ſee him appear with ſeven Stars in his right hand, and a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edged Sword going forth of his mouth: We ſee him clad with a robe dipt in blood, and mounted upon a white horſe: Wee ſee him in the ſhape of a Lamb ſlain, having ſeven eyes and ſeven horns. But we never
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33453:45"/>ſee him there, or in any other place of the holy Hiſtory, in the figure of his own naturall viſage: To teach us, That we ought rather to ſeek him in the deſcription of his graces, then in the Idea of the feature of his viſage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>What's the reaſon, that amongst all the wonders that God hath wrought, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made an Image to ſpeak?</head>
               <p>God hath ſhewed forth an infinite of Miracles of all ſorts, but never did he cauſe an Image to ſpeak. There were Cherubins within the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and in the Temple, and God cauſed his voice to be heard from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the mercy-ſeat, over which theſe Statues were placed; but wee read not that ever they ſpake word. The Son of God likewiſe never wrought any ſuch miracle, nor his Diſciples. God (without doubt) would not that men ſhould have this pretence to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour their Idolatry. For if any image
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33453:45"/>had ſpoken, they had eaſily beleeved that there had been ſome divine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue incloſed in ſuch a ſtatue. And that's the reaſon the Divel did that which God would not: for he hath often ſpake in divers Idols, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oblige men to conſult with, and ſerve them. In the 13 of the <hi>Revelat. verſ.</hi> 15. this Myſtery is counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that the ſecond beaſt wrought, that he made an Image ſpeak. Beſides, although God ſhould have made any ſpeak, (as many ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) yet ſhould it be no more ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſs, if it were again in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Two ſorts of ſinners at which God mocks.</head>
               <p>All ſinners are worthy of Gods anger; but there are two are worthy of deriſion, as well as his indignation: One is the proud; the other, the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later: and we read, that God mocks at both. At the proud; <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2. <hi>Hee that ſitteth in the heavens ſhall laugh at
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33453:46"/>them, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion. Eſa.</hi> 14. he jears the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> whoſe pride began to be followed with ruine. It ſeems alſo, that God mock'd at the pretenſions of our great Grand-father, when he ſaid, <hi>See, Man is become as one of us.</hi> He mocks like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at the Idolaters, Superſtitious, and thoſe that reſort to Wizzards. So ſaid he to the Iſraelites, whom he had chaſtened for their Idolatries, <hi>Cry to the gods ye have choſen, that they may deliver you, Judg.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.28. So the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> laughing at the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> bid them cry very loud, that that Idol might hear them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The admirable proportions that God holds in the diſpenſation of his judgements.</head>
               <p>Here is a point marvellous dark, and a matter whoſe bottom it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to ſound. Our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot conceive why God cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth one more then another; why
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33453:46"/>with ſuch a kinde of puniſhment; why ſooner or later; why in ſuch meaſure; why ſo long time, or ſo ſhort; and other reaſons of ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities as therein are marked. Yet this Soveraign Wiſdom doth nothing that is not perfectly regular, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his operations ſeem to us ſo out of order.</p>
               <p>Sometime God looks to the nature and quality of the crime. When we are in affliction, it is not enough for us to know or ſay in generall, that it is fallen upon us for our ſins: There are alwayes certain miſdeeds amongſt others, that are the particular cauſe of ſuch and ſuch judgements. So the Nations that God threatned by <hi>Amos, Chapt.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. were guilty of many enormous ſins; but there was one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt in every of them for which they were condemned. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> for having broken <hi>Galaad</hi> with harrows of iron: <hi>Gaza</hi> and <hi>Tyre,</hi> for having delivered over the Jews into Captivity: <hi>Edom,</hi> for having purſued
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33453:47"/>his Brother with the ſword: <hi>Moah,</hi> for having burned the bones of the King of <hi>Edom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sometimes God marks them that give the firſt example of evill, and handles them more harſhly: So <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo,</hi> becauſe it was the firſt Town that ſhut the gates againſt Iſrael, was expoſed unto unmercifulneſs: So <hi>Amalek,</hi> for being the firſt that made war upon the people of God, was condemned to a finall deſtruction: So <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> becauſe they were the firſt breakers of the Ceremoniall Law, after the eſtabliſhment of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> Prieſthood, were devoured by fire: So <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> the firſt that belied God in the beginnings of the Chriſtian Church, were miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Sometimes God hath regard unto the number of ſins; ſeldome doth he puniſh a man, or a people for one fault: When he adjudged the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, from twenty yeers old and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to die all in the wilderneſſe,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33453:47"/>that was by reaſon of a tenth Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſin that they had committed; for God already complained that they had tempted him ten times, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Sometimes God looks to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and meaſure of ſins, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears to puniſh them til they be come to a certain growth: He would not put <hi>Abraham</hi> into the poſſeſſion of the promiſed Land, becauſe that the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Amorites was not yet ful, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.16.</p>
               <p>Sometime God hath an eye to ſome circumſtance that concerns the crime: For the forty dayes that the Iſraelites had imployed to diſcover the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to an exile of forty yeers in the Deſert, in deteſtation of their murmuring, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34. For having neglected the Sabbath of the Land, which they ought to have let reſt once every ſeven yeers, they were captives out of their Land ſeventy yeers, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.21. King <hi>Hozias,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:33453:48"/>for having preſumed to enter into the holy place, and there taking upon him to execute the Office which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained not but to the Prieſts, was ſtricken with a diſeaſe, the judgment whereof belonged onely unto the Prieſts, <hi>viz.</hi> a Leproſie: and was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven not onely out of the Temple, but out of the ſociety of men.</p>
               <p>Sometime God imployes one evill doer to puniſh another, that hath committed the like offence. There is even a ſecret analogie and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie in ſuch judgements. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent had inticed man to deſpiſe the fruits that God had given him, and had drawn him to covet one that God had forbidden him. The Iſraelites deſpiſe the Manna, the ordinary food that God had given them, and coveted the fruits of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that God had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them. Their ſin, like that of the Serpent, was puniſhed by the biting of ſerpents that were ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.5, 6.</p>
               <p>Sometime God practiſeth the law
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33453:48"/>of retaliation, or otherwayes he ſends puniſhments anſwering the form or nature of the crime; we have an example in <hi>Adonibezek, Jud.</hi> 1.7. and infinite more both in Scripture and experience.</p>
               <p>Sometimes God looks upon the number of offenders, and of juſt men, and on the proportions which he findes between the offences of the one, and vertues of the other: had there been ten juſt men in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> it had not been deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Sometimes ſinners are handled according to the meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they have received; by this rule judgement begins at the houſe of God, and <hi>Jeroſalem</hi> was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the <hi>Pagan</hi> Nations. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Ier.</hi> 25.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes God looks upon the perſons of our Anceſtors from whom he takes occaſion to puniſh the children, chiefly when they fil up the meaſure of their Fathers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.32.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:33453:49"/>
               <p>Finally, though God puniſheth ſinners, yet he puniſheth them not alwayes for their ſins, but ſometimes for other cauſes, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.2, 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of whom are deſcended thoſe Nations that go aked?</head>
               <p>It is known there be many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among whom nakedneſs is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no diſgrace, a great part of the Inhabitants of <hi>Affris,</hi> and the Natives of the Weſt-<hi>Indies</hi> walk without any other covering then their skins, and it is remarkable that the people there, (at leaſt the <hi>Affricans</hi>) are come of <hi>Cham,</hi> one of <hi>Noahs</hi> three Sons. For the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Geneſis</hi> chap. 10. deſcribing the peopling of the World ſhortly after the Flood, makes it appear that the Poſterity of <hi>Cham</hi> did for the moſt part ſettle themſelves in <hi>Egypt, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> and other neighbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, whence doubtleſs they ſpred themſelves through all the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33453:49"/>of <hi>Affric,</hi> and the adjoining I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlands, and at laſt moved Weſtward: the brutiſh behaviour that is found at this day among theſe Nations, void of all ſhame, ſeems to have continued among them as a mark of their Grand-fathers impudence, who diſcovered his fathers naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22. and this is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that after ſo many ages, ſuch multitudes of people do yet expreſs the turpitude of an Anceſter remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo many degrees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The number of Generations named in this Promiſe.</head>
               <p>Many brethren are accounted but for one Generation, becauſe they are all within one degree of deſcent; ſo the 12. ſons of <hi>Iacob</hi> together were but one Generation, and which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. born after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge: for in the Genealogy of Gods people we finde after <hi>Arphaxad</hi> (the firſt that was born from the Flood)
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33453:50"/>12. Generations, till the 12. ſons of <hi>Iacob:</hi> to wit. 1. <hi>Arphaxad.</hi> 2. <hi>Scela.</hi> 3. <hi>Heber.</hi> 4. <hi>Peleg.</hi> 5. <hi>Rehu.</hi> 6. <hi>Serug.</hi> 7. <hi>Nacor.</hi> 8. <hi>Thera.</hi> 9. <hi>Abraham.</hi> 10. <hi>Iſaac.</hi> 11. <hi>Iacob.</hi> 12. the twelve Patriarchs. <hi>viz. Rubin, Simeon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now taking the Generations in this ſenſe, and reckoning them for ſo many degrees, we finde, that from the Creation till this preſent time, there have not been a thouſand Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations as yet; and indeed it is impoſſible there ſhould have been ſo many: For though every man that hath been ſince the Creation, ſhould have been a father at the age of ten years, in a continual ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet there cannot be ſix hundred Generations, compleat ſeeing the World hath not laſted ſix thouſand years as yet: but indeed the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Generations ſince <hi>Adam</hi> is far from a thouſand. Jeſus Chriſt, who was born a little before the four thouſand year of the World, was but the ſeventy fift Generation from
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33453:50"/>
                  <hi>Adam;</hi> as may be ſeen in his Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy; <hi>Luke</hi> 3.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by all which we may judge that the race from <hi>Adam</hi> will never reach till the thouſand Generation; or elſe the World muſt neceſſarily continue longer then hitherto it hath done, which is againſt all probability.</p>
               <p>But why then is it that God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to ſhew mercy unto the thouſand Generation, ſeeing that hath not yet been, nor (likely) ſhall ever be? The meaning is, that though the race of the faithful ſhould extend it ſelf to the thouſand Generation, yet Gods mercies would extend it ſelf as far.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Strange Exmples of divers Subjects, in which God hath manifeſted both his Mercy and Inſtice.</head>
               <p>God hath ſhew in both theſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of his joyntly, and yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, at the ſame time, and in the ſame reſpect. They have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33453:51"/>in heaven in <hi>Adams</hi> Family, in the Ark; in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Tent; in that of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> among the Apoſtles; and in the puniſhment of evil doers in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe places God hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted notable examples, both of his juſtice and mercy: in heaven the good Angels were elected, and the evil ſpirits driven thence; In <hi>Adams</hi> Family, we have <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain;</hi> God regarded the Oblation of the one, and rejected that of the other; in <hi>Noahs</hi> Family we have <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Cham,</hi> the one is bleſſed, the other accurſed; in the houſe of <hi>Abraham</hi> we finde <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael; Gal.</hi> 4. the one the child of promiſe. the other after the fleſh; in that of <hi>Iſaac</hi> we have <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> the one beloved of God, the other hated of him; among the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> there are <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Saul;</hi> the one according to Gods heart, the other rejected by God; among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iudas;</hi> the one was
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33453:51"/>received into mercy, the other pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in deſpair; on the very Croſs the two theeves, that were crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chriſt, one of them obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed grace, the other died in impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; the like we read in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Publican and Phariſee in the Temple, the one returning to his houſe juſtified, the other was left in his pride; ſo in the laſt day two ſhall be in the ſame bed, the one ſhall be received, and the other ſhall be forſaken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why did God ſometimes take ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care of the Patriarchs and their children, even of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat were wicked, and at this day h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes no ſuch addreſſes as he did th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to them?</head>
               <p>Surely the ſame affection that was in <hi>Hagar,</hi> when ſhe thought her ſon would die, may bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mothers, to whom notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God will ſend no Angels to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33453:52"/>aſſure their childrens lives, or their future proſperity; <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.15. &amp;c. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny women alſo may be paired with <hi>Rebecca,</hi> when they carry twins as ſhe did, and yet God will not ſend them an Oracle to let them know what ſhall befal their children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22. Now among divers reaſons of this extraordinary care which God had towards theſe perſons we muſt know, that in them were compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended whole Nations, which <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> bore in her womb; <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.23. we muſt not think it then ſtrange, for God to teſtifie a particular care of thoſe whom he had appointed to be the fathers of Nations: Beſides, thoſe twins muſt be conſidered in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother quality, to wit, as God would make them examples and types of the great miſtery of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reprobation, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 10. &amp;c. So <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael</hi> were marked by the hand of God to be figures of another Myſtery handled by the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33453:52"/>
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24. the nativity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of theſe perſons, and moſt of the actions which ſeemed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and ridiculous, were full of myſteries, for which cauſe God did extraordinarily preſerve and guide them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God ſpent but ſix daies in Creating the World, and employed ſeven to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the walls of <hi>Jerico?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This City which was the firſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> took in after their paſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Iordan,</hi> was delivered to them without ſtroke. The walls whereof were beaten down, not by Engines, nor overthrown by ſpringing of Mines, but onely by the preſence of the Ark of God, accompanied with ſeven Prieſts ſounding Trumpets of Rams horns, and compaſſing the City, by which means the whole walls fell down: But this proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on continued ſeven daies; for firſt they went about <hi>Ierico</hi> for the ſpace
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33453:53"/>of ſix daies, every day once; after this on the ſeventh day the Town was encompaſſed ſeven times; and at the ſeventh time, when the horns ſounded, and the people gave a ſhout for joy, the whole circuit of the walls fell down, ſo that the Town was wholly diſmantled, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Now among the moſt remarkable paſſages of this overthrow, it may be wondered, why God, who in a moment with the breath of his mouth can beat down the ſtrongeſt rampiers and fortifications, would imploy ſo many daies, and ſo long a train of reiterated formalities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the demolition of this place: and withall why this was not done till the ſeventh day, whereas the whole world was finiſhed in the ſpace of ſix daies. Muſt there be more time to deſtroy one Town, then to make the Univerſe? Surely in this example, as in infinite more, God would ſhew that his hand is
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33453:53"/>ſlower in demoliſhing, then in eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing in defacing the leaſt of his work, then in forming the greateſt thereof: and ſo that his juſtice reacheth no farther then the third or fourth Generation, whereas his mercy is extended to the thouſand Generation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="commandment">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33453:54"/>
            <head>The II. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God pronounceth the ſame word twice to the ſame purpoſe, againſt idle oathes?</head>
               <p>VVEE finde that when God ſpeaks to man he ſometimes doubleth his words. In mens ſpeeches thoſe repetitions ſerve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make the diſcourſe more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical, or to make a greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on the minde and memory of the hearer: but in Gods language they are of another importance; when God uttereth one and the ſame ſpeech twice, as it were with one continued threed, he ſheweth it is irrevocable, and no waies to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33453:54"/>be altered. We know that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God hath repealed, and annihilated his declaratory ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as that which was uttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ninivie,</hi> which he threatned after 40. daies to deſtroy, yet he ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her a long time after this: but when God uttereth a ſpeech twice together, he never revokes it: The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> willing to expreſs the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable ſtability of an Oracle: ſaith: <hi>God hath ſpoken twice, I have heard the ſame twice,</hi> Pſal. 62.12. that miraculous writing containing the ruine of <hi>Balthazer</hi> and his Kingdom, began with <hi>Mene, Mene, it is numbred, it is numbred;</hi> as if it would ſay, the reckoning is perfected, nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be accounted for, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.25. We read alſo that ſometimes God having expreſſed the ſame thing, by two different repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; this doubling thereof did ſignifie that the decree was irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s two diſtinct dreams were but one thing in ſubſtance;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33453:55"/>for the Kine in the one, and the Ears of corn in the other, did ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame thing, notwithſtanding this repetition of the ſame matter, although expreſſed under different figures, made <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſay, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the dream was doubled twice, the thing was eſtabliſhed by God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.32.</p>
               <p>Now it ſeems that Chriſt hath touched the ſame Myſtery, when he commands that our ſpeech ſhould be yea, yea, nay, nay, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.37. as if he would injoyn us to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a double affirmation, or a double negation, in liew of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous oaths, as being ſufficient to expreſs the ſtability of our ſpeeches, after the example of Almighty God, who never repeals what he hath twice pronounced together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33453:55"/>
               <head>Although in ſome things God hath diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his law, yet he hath never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with faith; alſo of the ſtability of Gods oathes.</head>
               <p>Againſt the General Law, God commanded <hi>Abraham</hi> to kill his own ſon, againſt the ſame Law God au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to retain the jewels and Garments which they borrowed of the <hi>Egyptians, Exod.</hi> 12.35, 36. but he never commanded or permitted, either to ſpeak or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve a falſhood, chiefly in Religion, the Commandments which forbad him are undiſpenſable, and theſe frauds which they call pious, are the more Criminal; for there is no thing more repugnant to Religion, then to ſupport her with lies, as it is alſo a horrid thing to violate faith under the ſhaddow of faith, that is to ſay of Religion.</p>
               <p>In brief, if any hath power and authority to diſpence with an oath,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33453:56"/>ſurely it is God, but this he never did, for when he ſwares a thing, he never revokes it: The Lord hath ſworn and will not repent: if there God never diſpenſe with an oath, why ſhould any man dare to take upon him this power of diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either in himſelf or towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="commandment">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33453:56"/>
            <head>The IV. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Remember the Sabbath day,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God never wrought any miracle an the Sabbath day, before the coming of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THE Old Teſtament is full of Miracles, divers whereof were done among the Patriarchs, in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the deſart, in the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and even in the Captivity of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> yet we do not read, that any of them were wrought upon the Sabbath day: but on the contrary we finde that the miracle of the Manna which laſted forty years, was interrupted and ſuſpended every Sabbath; for the food which fell the ſix firſt daies of the week ceaſed on
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33453:57"/>the ſeventh, ſo that upon that day this miracle failed: It is true, that the conſequences and effects of a miracle hath ſometimes paſſed on the Sabbath; as the faſtings of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Eliah</hi> which laſted forty daies, in which time there were many Sabbaths; but this long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, was onely the effect of a ſupernatural vertue which God had beſtowed on them; now this gift in which conſiſted the miracle, was not found to be given on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day; otherwiſe in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the ſacred Hiſtory would not have omitted this cicumſtance in brief, 'tis impoſſible to they, that under the Old Teſtament any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle hath been wrought on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, whereas the new T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment obſerveth that this day wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for many miracles. If <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Eliah,</hi> or any of the Prophets had done any miracle upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, the Phariſees had not ſo boldly condemned the Son of God
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33453:57"/>for violating the Sabbath, ſeeing he wrought miracles on that day; and he had not failed in this point to have produced examples, if there had been any; but he indeed was the firſt that ever did any miracle on the Sabbath.</p>
               <p>This then that ſeemed to ſerve as a pretext for their reproof of Chriſt, was rather a means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to admire him ſo much the more; for this was an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary miracle, and a marke of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity far ſurpaſſing that of all the Prophets, by making that to be ſeen which none of them ever did; <hi>viz.</hi> To produce miracles on the Sabbath day; In a word, this was one of the prerogatives which God had reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for his Son, and one of the works by which God would have it known, that he was Lord of the Sabbath, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.8. To this I will add the enſuing obſervation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:33453:58"/>
               <head>Seven Sabbath daies which Chriſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his miracles.</head>
               <p>I will not ſpeak of that which is known to all; namely, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reckoning the Sabbath of every ſeventh day, there were beſides ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven daies yearly, in divers ſeaſons, on which all ſervile work was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid by the Law, theſe were the firſt and laſt of the feaſt of unleaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bread, that of the firſt fruits, that of the feaſt of Trumpets, the firſt and eighth of the feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, and that of Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: all theſe univerſary daies are mentioned in the 23. chapters of <hi>Leviticus;</hi> we know alſo that in the feaſts of Eaſter and Pentecoſt there were ſeven daies of reſt.</p>
               <p>But as the actions and ſufferings of Chriſt are the perfection of all thoſe things which are contained in the Old Teſtament, this ſeems to me worthy of admiration, that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33453:58"/>among the Sabbath daies which our Saviour honoured whileſt he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed in this world, the Hiſtory of the Goſpel hath marked out ſeven, which Chriſt made famous by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; I will ſet them down accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order of time, in which they fell out.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe ſeven daies of Sabbath was ſanctified by the cure of a Demoniac, of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s mother in law, and of ſome other infirm per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.31.</p>
               <p>The ſecond by a wonderful cure of the Paralitic, who had been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed thirty eight years, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>The third by the healing of him who had a whithered hand, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p>The fourth by the curing of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſick perſons, notwithſtanding the incredulity of the Galileans, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.1.</p>
               <p>The ſift by an unheard of miracle til then; a man born blind, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his ſight, <hi>John</hi> 9.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33453:59"/>
               <p>The ſixth by another ſtrange mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of a woman that was bowed downward eighteen years, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of this infirmity, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.10.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh by the cure of an Hydropic, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.1.</p>
               <p>So in Chriſt we have the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the Sabbath, ſanctified by thoſe actions, which before were never ſeen upon that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In what things our Saviour is to be immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</head>
               <p>God doth binde us to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Sabbath by his own example, becauſe he reſted himſelf on that day: but muſt we immitate God in all his actions; there be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in him which we cannot immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate without ſin or madneſs: to immitate his power, were not a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but an inſufferable pride, as that of <hi>Salmonius,</hi> or the King of <hi>Tyre, Ezek.</hi> 28.2. They that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to faſt forty daies after the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33453:59"/>example of the Son of God, ought to conſider that this faſt was one of the effects of his power, which we ought to admire, for we cannot i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate it: and here let us obſerve, that among all the perfections in God, there is not any one of them propoſed for our imitation, but his goodneſs; he never commanded us to follow his example, but in this one vertue; <hi>Be ye holy, as I am holy; Be merciful, as your Heavenly Father is merciful; Be perfect</hi> (to wit, in goodneſs) <hi>as your Father is perfect, Lev.</hi> 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and 6. So the ſanctification of the Sabbath conſiſteth chiefly in the action of goodneſs and holineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whence it is that in the Hiſtory of the New Teſtament, we do not read that ever the <hi>Sadduces</hi> appeared on the Sabbath day?</head>
               <p>There is nothing more frequent in the Goſpel, then the proceedings
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33453:60"/>of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> chiefly on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath daies: for on that day they are ſeen in the Temple, in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, even in the fields, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.1.2. on that day they are heard to cenſure the works of the Son of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.14.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.7. On that day they viſited and feaſted each other. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But for the <hi>Sadduces</hi> that other famous ſect, the ſacred Hiſtory makes no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, when it ſpeaks of any thing that paſt on the Sabbath day; it relates what they ſpoke or did in many occurrences upon divers daies, but it never ſpeaks of any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance they made that day; ſo that although ſometimes the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi> have been found to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the ſame place, yet this was never on the Sabbath; for we do not read that upon this day they ever met, nor that then the <hi>Sadduces</hi> diſputed with Chriſt, or cenſured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is actions, or that they came i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to the fields to calumniate them, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33453:60"/>with the Sabbath, which the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were wont to do; and which is ſtrange in the whole Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Goſpel, we do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nde that the <hi>Sadduces</hi> were ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Temple or Syn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Now to know the reaſon hereof we muſt preſuppoſe that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome have gathered out of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, that the <hi>Sadduces</hi> held among other of their errors, this, that it was not lawful to go out of their houſes on the Sabbath day into any place whatſoever: this opinion was grounded on a falſe expoſition of that paſſage in the Law, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that none ſhould go out of his houſe on the ſeventh day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.29. The <hi>Sadduces</hi> inferred upon this, that if any did but ſtep out from the door of his houſe on that day, he broke the Sabbath: The <hi>Phariſees</hi> on the other ſide proved, that upon the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day, they were bound to repair to the Temple and Synagogues; becauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33453:61"/>that on the Sabbath day the people ſhould aſſemble together, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.3. Yet notwithſtanding, the <hi>Sadduces</hi> upon that day would not go out of their houſes; whence it is that in all the ſacred Story, we do not finde that ever they ſhewed themſelves on the Sabbath day.</p>
               <p>In brief, under pretence of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving punctually the Sabbath, they profaned it impudently, in an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious idleneſs, and impious Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why the Law uſeth ſuch an excellent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. <hi>viz.</hi> God's Reſt, as a reaſon for the beaſts to reſt?</head>
               <p>The ſame reaſon why God will have man to reſt on the ſeventh day, obligeth him to ſuffer his ox and his aſſe, and all his cattle to reſt then: <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe upon that day God reſted; but why will Almighty God bring his own example, as a reaſon for the reſt of beaſts, a ſubject ſo
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33453:61"/>mean? Indeed humanity may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us to give reſt to the poor beaſts that travel for us; but doeth this baſe ſubject of the beaſts reſt, deſerve ſo noble and excellent a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as the reſt of God himſelf?</p>
               <p>We muſt obſerve here, one threed of the Lawgivers wiſdom. The Law of God contains many points, which would be contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe of their meanneſs, if there were not ſome proviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this: now to prevent this ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, God hath authoriſed them by the higheſt reaſons that can be, by the ſevereſt comminations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that infringe them, and by the richeſt promiſes to thoſe that obſerve them: this is the reaſon why ſuch grievous puniſhments are ſet down againſt him that ſhall taſte leavened bread within the ſeven daies of Eaſter; this is the reaſon why that he who findes a birds neſt muſt content himſelf with the young ones, and let the dam fly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33453:62"/>away, hath the promiſe of length of daies, which is the ſame that is annexed to one of the great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of the Law, for thoſe who honour their Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.6, 7. This is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why God forbids the eating of the fleſh of creeping things, and backs this prohibition with a reaſon taken from his own example, <hi>Be you</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>holy, becauſe I am holy, Lev.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> This is alſo the cauſe why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſeth his own example, in commanding the reſt of beaſts, for this ordinance being made in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of ſo mean a ſubject, is the more conſiderable, in that it is annexed to ſuch an high and excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to wit, the reſt that God took after the Creation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why none of the dead have been raiſed on the Sabbath day?</head>
               <p>In my obſervations on the Creed, upon the Articles of Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33453:62"/>I promiſed to handle this queſtion: I muſt firſt then verifie the Hypotheſis. I ſay that on the Sabbath day our Saviour cured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes, but never upon that day raiſed any that were dead, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Old nor New Teſtament do we read of any ſuch reſuſcitation upon that day. Not the Sunaimtes ſon, that was raiſed by <hi>Eliſha,</hi> for the Hiſtory ſaith expreſly, that it was not the Sabbath day, and the journey of <hi>Eliſha</hi> and <hi>Gehazi,</hi> which they made, to raiſe the dead child, was againſt the reſt of this day; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither he who was laid in the grave of the ſame Prophet, nor the ſons of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Nain,</hi> which were carrying to be buried, for they raiſed them there when they went to inter them: now the ſanctity of the Sabbath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred them from burying on that day, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.15. Not <hi>Lazarus</hi> of <hi>Bethany,</hi> for when he was raiſed, many Jews were come to his
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33453:63"/>grave, which the holineſs of the Sabbath would not have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Thoſe pious women who had prepared ſpices to embalm our Saviour's body, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the Sabbath, reſted all that day, and went not to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre till the next morning, which was the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> day after his death: not that thoſe were raiſed with Chriſt, and appeared in the holy City, for theſe miracles fell not out, till the day after the Sabbath: not the daughter of <hi>Iairus,</hi> nor <hi>Tabitha,</hi> for then they were raiſed, when their Friends were performing their Funeral Ceremonies for them: Now theſe actions, ſuch as are the burying of their dead, the waſhing and embalming of them, yea, the entring into an houſe where a dead corps lay, all theſe were prohibited on the Sabbath, as being incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with its ſanctity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 92.3. <hi>&amp;c. Acts</hi> 9.37. Not the Widow of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repta's</hi> ſon, whoſe reſurrection is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33453:63"/>mentioned without naming the day, which had not been omitted, if it had been on the Sabbath; not <hi>Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> who was raiſed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for this was on the firſt day of the week, the Sabbath being already paſt; and here it is remarkable, that this young man, the laſt of thoſe that were raiſed, recovered life the ſame day that Chriſt returned from the dead. <hi>viz.</hi> on the <hi>Sunday.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now why God never raiſed any on the Sabbath day, two reaſons may be given.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, becauſe Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is the firſt born among the dead, and the chief of thoſe that were raiſed, was not reſuſcitated on the Sabbath, but he ſuffered this day to paſs before he would come out of his grave; beſides, (as I obſerved on the Creed) Chriſt was not raiſed on the Sabbath to ſhew the union between him and others that were raiſed, of all which, none received life this day.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33453:64"/>
               <p>The other reaſon may be this, <hi>viz.</hi> This life is a time of travel, and the Sabbath was the time of reſt, the wiſdom of God would not that on the day which was ordained for the repoſe and reſt of the living, the dead ſhould be taken from their eaſe, and called back again to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="commandment">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:33453:64"/>
            <head>The V. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whence comes it as they ſay commonly, That Love and Affection uſeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend: Difference between Faith &amp; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: The words of <hi>Mal. 4.5.</hi> diſcuſſed.</head>
               <p>VVE know why God the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver hath ordained the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Children towards their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but hath not expreſſed the duty of Fathers towards their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; the reaſon is, becauſe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Parents towards their Children is naturally greater, and needs fewer incitements then that of Children towards their Parents; this is the meaning of that common ſaying; that the Parents affection
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33453:65"/>deſcends towards the Children, but the love of Children towards their Parents doth not ſo eaſily aſcend.</p>
               <p>Now we demand, how comes it that love rather deſcends then aſcends? The reaſon is, becauſe Love had its beginning in Heaven; God is the firſt that loved. I ſay Love had its original in Heaven, and came down into the Earth; and in this it differs from Faith, which had its beginning on Earth, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates in Heaven. By a ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and natural affection, which is found in paternity, imitates that of God, which is Father of all, and who loved us before we loved him; as in affection the Father prevents the Child; ſo the Love of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, doth infinitely ſurpaſs that which we bear towards him.</p>
               <p>The Prophet in that paſſage which I quoted, ſpeaking of the reuniting of diſagreeing Families, ſaith, <hi>That the heart of the Fathers ſhall be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towards their Children, and the heart
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33453:65"/>of the Children towards their Fathers.</hi> In the order of theſe words, the converſion of the Father towards the Child proceeds the converſion of the Child towards the Father; for we muſt preſuppoſe, that as the Paternal affection is the firſt and ſtrongeſt, ſo the heart of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is more eaſily reconciled, and ſooner appeaſed then that of the Child.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why the Law expreſſeth the Childrens du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Parents by the word <hi>Honour,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by the word <hi>Love.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Surely the Honour which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be rendred to them, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not exclude the Love which is due to them: But whereas unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures Love their little ones, and are beloved of them: The Lawgiver wills that this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral affection, which ought to be in Man, ſhould be cloathed with a more noble quality, then that which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33453:66"/>is found among beaſts; for theſe are capable of natural affections, but man alone is capable of Honour; as well to give Honour, as to receive it.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon why this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment ſpeaks of Honour rather then of Love, in ſome regard a man owes more affection to his wife and children, then to his father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for he muſt forſake father and mother, and cleave to his wife; but in matter of Honour, the Parents have alwaies the preheminence; in our affections many times they have the ſecond place, but in Honour and reverence they ſhould ſtill be firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Wherefore the Law commanded Children to fear thoſe that brought them into the world, namely, the Mother before the Father.</head>
               <p>The Decalogue ſaith, <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother;</hi> but in the 19.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33453:66"/>of <hi>Leviticus</hi> ver. 3. it is ſaid that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſhould fear his Mother and his Father; here the Mother is firſt named: We muſt obſerve that in this paſſage the Law giver ſpeaks of the fear which the children ſhould have towards thoſe that are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of their Generation. The love which they carry to the child, cauſes ſometimes that he fears them not, therefore God commands him to fear them. Now becauſe the Mother hath the greateſt part of this natural affection towards the child, and conſequently is leſs feared; God hath inforced this obligation of the child towards the Mother, naming her firſt, before the Father in this commandment, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyneth to fear them both: So this duty towards the Mother, being more ſubject to be infringed, is made ſo much conſiderable, in that it is put in the firſt place.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33453:67"/>
            <head>The Promiſe annexed to the fift Commandment.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Examples, of that propertion which is found ſometimes between good works, and the recompence which they receive in this life.</head>
               <p>IT is well known why God in this Commandment, hath rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed life, then any other bleſſing. From our Parents we have received our life, hence it is that life is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to him, that ſhall Honour thoſe of whom he hath received it; for as the puniſhment ſometime an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the offence, by the Law of retaliation, even ſo many times God remunerates a good work, by ſome favour anſwering the ſame in ſome ſimilitude: So <hi>Abraham</hi> offered his onely ſon, and God promiſed him
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33453:67"/>thouſands of children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17. So <hi>Jacob,</hi> who had fed <hi>Joſeph</hi> by the ſpace of ſeventeen yeers, was reciprocally fed by <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> the ſpace of ſeventeen yeers: So <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> for their Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to men, had the honour to entertain Angels: So <hi>Rachab</hi> having preſerved the Spies in her houſe, was her ſelf preſerved with her houſe: So the houſe of <hi>Obed Edom</hi> was bleſſed for having received the Ark of God: ſo <hi>Ezechias</hi> having rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned 14 years religiouſly, received from God an addition of fifteen years, a tearm longer then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: So <hi>Daniel</hi> and his fellowes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to deſile themſelves with the King of <hi>Babylons</hi> meat, though they were fed onely with pulſe and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet they fared better then thoſe that were fed with the Kings allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: So ſhe that was blamed for pouring out a precious ointment on our Saviours head, is praiſed at this day, where ever the Goſpel is
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33453:68"/>preached: So many for humbling themſelves have been exalted. 'Its true we finde not alwayes this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion between the work and the reward: but though God doth not ſtill pay in the ſame kind, yet he gives that which is equivalent, yea, infinitely better; if he doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow long life upon Earth, he gives that which is eternal in Heaven. Now why he gives to ſome a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to others a ſhorter life, there be other reaſons. but ſecret, I will obſerve ſome examples.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why fifteen years were added to the life of <hi>Ezechias.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>He that could ſee the particular cauſes why God abridges and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs our life till ſuch a minute of time, will finde the effects of a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous diſpenſation. The number of the years of the Patriarchs, and many others famous in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, is full of ſuch Myſteries.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33453:68"/>take one which is notable. We know that God having cauſed the ſentence of death to be pronounced againſt <hi>Ezechias,</hi> did notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding add fifteen yeers to his life: The common ſort, who ſee no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the ſuperficies of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, perceive not of what impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, this tearm of years was, which God beſtowed on this Prince; this number of years was fignificative, and carrieth a meaning that reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth far.</p>
               <p>We muſt obſerve that a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ezechias</hi> ſickneſs, the Kingdom of <hi>Juda</hi> was drawing towards its end; it had been invaded by the Aſſyrians, and as yet ſtood in aw of them; for this cauſe God promiſeth to <hi>Ezechias,</hi> not onely the prolonga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his life, but alſo the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his Kingdom; for at the ſame time that he aſſured his life for fifteen years, he added, that he would deliver him from the hands of the Aſſyrians, and would defend
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33453:69"/>
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the capital City; ſo the fifteen years that were promiſed to <hi>Ezechias</hi> did expreſs alſo the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance and eſtabliſhment of his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>We muſt obſerve then that <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias</hi> was the fifteenth King that raigned in <hi>Iudea,</hi> in which the true religion was preſerved; for from <hi>Saul,</hi> who was the firſt King, till <hi>Ezechias</hi> incluſively are reckoned fifteen Kings of <hi>Iuda;</hi> to wit, 1. <hi>Saul.</hi> 2. <hi>David.</hi> 3. <hi>Salomon.</hi> 4. <hi>Roboam,</hi> who was forſaken by the twelve Tribes, and retained onely that of <hi>Iuda,</hi> with a part of <hi>Benjamin.</hi> 5. <hi>Abija.</hi> 6. <hi>Aſa.</hi> 7. <hi>Ioſophat.</hi> 8. <hi>Ioram.</hi> 9. <hi>Achaziah,</hi> otherwaies called <hi>Hozias,</hi> whom his mother <hi>Athalia</hi> followed, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe uſurped the Kingdom, her unlawful ragin is not counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the true Kings. 10. <hi>Ioas.</hi> 11. <hi>Amaziah.</hi> 12. <hi>Hazaria.</hi> 13. <hi>Iotham.</hi> 14. <hi>Achaz.</hi> 15. <hi>Ezechias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As then the raign of <hi>Ezechias</hi> was the fifteenth in order of ſucceſſion,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33453:69"/>ſo God would give him fifteen years, including as it were in this epitome, all the former raigns, and recapitulating them by the like number of years in the fifteenth King; this was to confirm al together both the life and raign of <hi>Ezechias,</hi> both which having been upon the point of expiration; ſo that the life of this Prince being prolonged fifteen years, was a pledge of the ſubſiſtance of that throne which had ſupported fifteen Kings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The age of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when they paſſed out of the Wilderneſs into the Land of Promiſe.</head>
               <p>This I obſerve here as an Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal circumſtance only. None of thoſe who entered into <hi>Canaan</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter the death of <hi>Moſes,</hi> had as yet attain'd the age of ſixty years, except <hi>Calib</hi> and <hi>Ioſua,</hi> whom God reſerved as two ancient witneſſes of the wonders he wrought in <hi>Egypt.</hi> This may be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33453:70"/>eaſily verified; for two years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> departure from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> they were all condemned to die in the deſert, except ſuch as were then twenty yeers old and under, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.29, 30. ſince this ſentence of condemnation there paſſed thirty eight years, in which the ſentence was performed, and about the end of this tearm, the ſurvivers entred <hi>Canaan;</hi> now if we add the twenty years of their life, when God utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this ſentence, to the thirty eight years of their wandring in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, it will appear that all thoſe who entred the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſua</hi> were under ſixty yeers; ſo that there was none who was decrepit with age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The meaſure and proportion of mans life from time to time, ſince the firſt ages.</head>
               <p>There are ſix degrees by which the life of man hath been altered
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33453:70"/>ſince our firſt Parents.</p>
               <p>Firſt, before the Flood the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of mans years was at moſt nine hundred, or nine hundred and ſixty, as we may ſee in <hi>Iered</hi> and <hi>Methuſala, Gen.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Secondly, After the Flood imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, God altered the third part of that age, for <hi>Sem</hi> the moſt famous of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Sons, lived in all but ſix hundred years.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In the firſt Generations of thoſe who were born after the Flood, the life of man was abridged one moiety: for <hi>Arphaxad, Scelas, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> lived but four hundred thirty eight, or four hundred ſixty four years, whereas their firſt progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors had lived twice as long.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this half was cut in two about the time of the Tower of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel;</hi> ſo that mans life was abridged to the fourth part of the ordinary age of the firſt men: for <hi>Peleg</hi> who was born at that time lived 239. year, which was but the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33453:71"/>fourth part of the years of <hi>Jered</hi> and <hi>Methuſala.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, afterwards the life of man was yet much more ſhortned, and ſtill declining through many genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, reached but to the eighth part of the age of our firſt Parents. This was in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who lived one hundred and twenty years, which is but the eighth part of nine hundred and ſixty: By the way we may obſerve, that when God was to ſend the Flood, he gave to men but the tearm of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty years, which was the eighth part of the ordinary age of men in thoſe times, to which it ſeems anſwers the number of eight perſons ſaved in the Ark.</p>
               <p>Sixtly and laſtly, the life of man grew every day ſhorter and ſhorter, till it was reduced to the twelf part of the firſt meaſure; for eighty years, which is the age that few at this day do exceed, is but the twelf part of nine hundred and ſixty;
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33453:71"/>which was then the ordinary age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Flood, and that which was then, their youthful age, is now our greateſt old age.</p>
               <p>So then the life of man was firſt reduced to two thirds, then to the half, then to the fourth, then to the eighth part, and in the end to the twelfth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>None of the Kings of <hi>Juda</hi> exceeded the age of ſeventy years.</head>
               <p>This is but an Hiſtorical obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet remarkable, that theſe very Kings which God had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over his people, have been all ſhort lived: he that lived longeſt was <hi>David;</hi> he was thirty years old when he was ſet on his throne, and he raigned forty years and ſix months; ſo that he did not much exceed ſeventy years, but none of his ſucceſſors from <hi>Salomon</hi> till <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> did ever attain to that age; which may be eaſily proved by the ſacred Chronology.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:33453:72"/>
               <head>Difference between the faithful of the Old Teſtament, and thoſe of the New, concerning their deſire of long life: another difference about the reckoning of the years of their life.</head>
               <p>Under the Old Teſtament many of the faithful deſired long life, but ſince the coming of Chriſt, we do not read of any who have deſired it: on the contrary, when <hi>Simeon</hi> had ſeen Chriſt the Lord, he was content to die: after that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of eternal life appeared, the faithful have not had ſuch deſire to ſtay long in this tranſitory life; and ſo much the leſs, in that our Saviour did not ſojourn long in this world, having continued but few years.</p>
               <p>We may obſerve alſo, that the Old Teſtament ſpeaking of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the faithful, recites how many years they lived: but ſince the coming of our Lord, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed ſo ſhort a time upon the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33453:72"/>Earth, the ſacred ſtory makes no mention at all, of the total ſum of any mans years in all the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the daughter of <hi>Iairus</hi> is the onely perſon whoſe age is obſerved when ſhe died, but this was becauſe ſhe was reſtored again to life the ſame day, her departure having immediately followed upon her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Three cauſes, why men are loath to leave this life, repreſented in him who died firſt.</head>
               <p>The trouble that men have upon the apprehenſion of death, is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the concurrence of theſe cauſes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if one die young; for he hath more reaſon to deſire life, then he who is full and ſatisfied with daies.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if he die a violent death, for we are beſt content with that which is natural.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:33453:73"/>
               <p>Thirdly, if he die without iſſue; for death ſhould be more ſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe who ſurvive themſelves in the perſons of their children.</p>
               <p>Now that we may in good time learn, that neither the ſhortneſs of this life, nor violent death, nor want of poſterity, ſhould make our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture grievous to us, God would have theſe three accidents to meet in him, who was both a juſt man and the firſt that died, to wit, <hi>Abel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For firſt, he died young in regard of the age of men in thoſe daies.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he dies a violent death; and which was moſt grievous, by the hand of his own brother.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he died without iſſue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A moral obſervation upon the daies of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> raiſed from the dead.</head>
               <p>The number of daies makes not a long life; many who think they are alive, are dead in effect, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6. the daies we paſs in ignorance or in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33453:73"/>malice, ſhould be abated from the count of our years. The four daies of <hi>Lazarus</hi> his abode among the dead; muſt not be reckoned among the daies of his life; and whereas he was raiſed again, he had reaſon to reckon from the day of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, rather then from the day of his nativity.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="commandment">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:33453:74"/>
            <head>The VI. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God in his titles doeth rather call Himſelf our <hi>Buckler,</hi> then our <hi>Sword.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHEN the Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Gods protection, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his arms to our enemies, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents them rather defenſive then offenſive; ſometimes he is called the Rock and Tower of his people, ſometimes alſo our, Buckler; this was the firſt title that God aſſumed to himſelf, after the firſt war we read was in the world, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. for thus he vouchſafes to ſpeak to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, I am thy Buckler;</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he hath been many times ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by this title, in that he
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33453:74"/>would be called the Buckler of his people; but he would never be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their ſword, but once, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he was named their Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>Deut</hi> 33.29. this is to ſhew that the children of God are not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quarrellers, and if at any time they take arms, it is rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend then to hurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Since <hi>Moſes</hi> there have been but three men, who received power to kill any miraculouſly; and the ſame who have miraculouſly inflicted death on the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, have alſo given life to the dead. Reaſons of the one and the other.</head>
               <p>Among the miracles that God hath diſplayed by his ſervants, we read that ſometimes they have put ſome perſons to death, ſo <hi>Elijah</hi> made fire come down from heaven, which conſumed two Companies of fifty men a peece, with their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; ſo <hi>Eliſha</hi> cauſed Bears to come out of the Forreſt, which tore
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33453:75"/>many of the Children of <hi>Bethel;</hi> ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> by his word onely ſmote with death <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira.</hi> Theſe Executions could not be but juſt, being done by a ſupernatural power; notwithſtanding God did not beſtow this, but on very few; for ſince <hi>Moſes,</hi> though many have had the gift of miracles, yet none have received this power of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men by miracles, but theſe three, <hi>Elijah, Eliſha,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter;</hi> neither would God have thoſe, in whom he had placed this miraculous power, to make uſe thereof but very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: therefore Chriſt did juſtly reprove the Apoſtles, who would have imitated this Act of <hi>Elijah, Luke</hi> 9.54, 55. Moreover, thoſe whom God had employed to inflict death upon ſome, he gave them power to beſtow life upon others; as <hi>Elijah</hi> on the Widows ſon of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repta; Eliſha</hi> on the <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſon, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> on <hi>Tabitha,</hi> as being an Act more glorious to beſtow life on
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33453:75"/>the dead, then to take it from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; he would alſo ſhew, that for the more full authoriſing of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of theſe great perſonages, they were employed as well to give life, as to deſtroy; otherwiſe, wicked men would have had ſome pretence in ſaying, that their God had power to kill the living, but not to reſtore the dead; which blaſphemy was prevented by the wiſdome of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The plot of the Prieſts in conſulting to put <hi>Lazarus</hi> to death, <hi>Joh. 12.10.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Murther is more or leſs enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in divers reſpects, now though the example which I ſet down here be extraordinary, it will ſerve ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs to ſhew how far the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit of murther extends it ſelf. The ſon of God had raiſed one that was dead, the Prieſts endeavoured to bury this miracle, willing to ſend back to the grave a man that had
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33453:76"/>been thence taken out, this was to commit a double murther upon the ſame perſon; as God had given twice life to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> (the one at his nativity, the other at his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſo this was as it were to make him die twice, in taking from him the ſecond life, which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed in the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A queſtion: If the puniſhment of a criminal being interrupted by ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary accident intervening, after the execution is begun, is it juſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him, of the puniſhment to which he was condemmed.</head>
               <p>It hath hapned ſometimes, that malefactors have fallen down from the Gibet upon the breaking of the rope, ſome have been taken down as dead, who yet have lived a good while after; ſome upon the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold have had divers blowes in the neck by the ſword, and yet the head not cut off. St. <hi>Ierem</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Innocent</hi> mentions a ſtrange exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33453:76"/>and in the former age, one of our Martyrs being ſet upon the pile, where they thought to have burnt him alive, he died a natural and quiet death, before the fire was kindled.</p>
               <p>But if it happen that a Malefactor who hath paſſed through all the ſorts of a mortal execution ſhould be yet found alive by ſome means not thought on, or foreſeen by men; ought he be again expoſed to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment? The providence of God who hath reſcued him, ſeems to have given him letters of pardon: Juſtice alſo which did not condemn him to die twice ſeems to have received the ſatisfaction, which it required of him, ſeeing he hath undergone, if not death it ſelf, yet at leaſt the impreſſion of death.</p>
               <p>In this caſe, which may furniſh matter for a fair debate, I diſtingiſh thus: there be ſome crimes ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormous, that they deſerve more deaths then one, if a man could die
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33453:77"/>oftner then once; ſo murtherers, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, and others guilty of ſuch hainous wickedneſs, ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried back again to puniſhment, though they had been reſcued by ſome interruption which might ſeem miraculous; it is to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that the juſtice of God, did ſtay the courſe of execution to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe rather the pain of death, then to remit the puniſhment; but as for leſſer faults, chiefly thoſe which Gods law hath not declared capital, and yet are ſuch by the civil law, as theft, it ſeems that the Malefactor hath ſufficiently ſuffered pain, if he hath taſted the half of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An alluſion in the Apoſtles words, who ordains that the Sun go not down upon our anger, <hi>Epheſ. 4.26.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The law commands that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors body put to death, be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the ſame day; it is expreſly forbid to let it hang all night on the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33453:77"/>Gallows <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.23. therefore as the Sun muſt not go down upon ſuch a ſpectacle, though it be the body of a Malefactor juſtly puniſhed by death, and whoſe puniſhment ſhould ſerve for an example: Even ſo, our anger, though it proceed from a juſt reſent of ſome injury done to us, yet it ſhould never ſleep with us; to this it ſeems the Apoſtles words do allude.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="commandment">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:33453:78"/>
            <head>The VII. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God though he approves not Poligamy nor unlawful diverces, which were free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the old Teſtament, yet never forbad them, but by the laſt of all the Prophets?</head>
               <p>THE queſtion is not why God tolerated theſe ſins among the Iſraelites. We know that the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts, did as it were extort this licence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.8. and for the ſame cauſe God did for a long time wink at this diſorder, which was ſo common: For we do not read that he ever reproved any of thoſe who had plurality of wives, or who put them away without juſt cauſe: onely in <hi>Malachi</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 14, &amp;c.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:33453:78"/>He cenſureth their Poligamy, and unlawful divorces. But why this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome which had been allowed by ſo long ſilence, and preſcription of ſo many ages, was condemned at laſt? Or why did he delay to cenſure this cuſtome, till the laſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; for <hi>Malachi</hi> was the laſt of them all.</p>
               <p>The purpoſe of God was, that the Kingdom of Chriſt ſhould be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous; amongſt other preheminences for its exact policy, far exceeding that which went before; for this end he ſuffered that of <hi>Moſes</hi> to give way to ſome diſorders, ſuch as were Poligamy and Divorces, to make it known, that the government of Chriſt which cut off this tolleration, is more perfect then that of <hi>Moſes:</hi> So that this politick Law of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſerved to declare and advance that peece of holineſs in Chriſt, and to ſhew the perfection of his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then, when he came to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the abuſe which that ancient
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33453:79"/>indulgence had ſupported.</p>
               <p>Now as the time of his coming, and of this reformation did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, God would prepare the hearts of men: and whereas he was to put a period to the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and meant not to ſend any more Prophets, it was needful that the laſt of them ſhould make this preparation: So as for Poligamy and unjuſt Divorces, God did not prohibit them ſooner, untill the Common-wealth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was to give a luſtre to that of Chriſt, ſhould have its period; and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he would not put an end to the Old Teſtament until he had diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed men to that reformation, which was to follow the coming of the Meſſiah; for after God was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the Fleſh, men have been ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a more exact purity; to this Chriſtians are more bound, then the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> or <hi>Patriarhs</hi> were.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:33453:79"/>
               <head>VVhy men are more ſubject to be aſhamed in the Act of any ſin, rather then in that of pride; and why more in Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, then in any other ſin?</head>
               <p>There is no ſin of which man is not aſhamed in the act thereof, or whilſt he is committing it. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bluſh when they lie or ſteal, or when they ſhew themſelves ſordid and cloſe fiſted, or when they play the Gluttons, and ſo in any other vitious act, although there be none to witneſs it. Onely the proud man ſins ſtill without ſhame; never was ſhame found in the act of pride. The reaſon hereof is, becauſe the glory which a proud man affects or preſumes to have in any action, is formally repugnant to ſhame: For it is impoſſible a man ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of that, which he eſteems tendeth to his glory.</p>
               <p>As for the other queſtion, we may ſay, that the more beſtial a ſin
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33453:80"/>is, it is the more ſubject to ſecret ſhame: for the ſin that reduceth a man to beaſt-like conditions, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to check him for the indignity and diſgrace he offereth to himſelf: Now as venereal Luxury is the moſt brutiſh of all ſins, ſo man is moſt naturally aſhamed of it; as for ſuch as have no ſhame, they are either innocents or beaſts: innocency is in infants, beaſtiality in ſavages, and ſuch as have loſt their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and in thoſe alſo that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent in their turpitude, ſuch as the <hi>Cyniks</hi> were.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>What may be inferred upon this, that the Holy Ghoſt deſcribing under divers ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes the ſpiritual beauty of the Church, makes no mention of painting?</head>
               <p>The ornaments of the Spouſe are miſtically repreſented in divers paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Scripture, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. In the <hi>Canticles;</hi> In <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13. There ſhe is ſet out in her chief
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33453:80"/>apparel, both in regard of the ſtuff, and the faſhion. Silk, Gold, Silver, pretious Stones, Pendants from the eares, Chains, Bracelets, the Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and all things which ſerve for advantaging a natural beauty, may be read among the ornaments of the Church: but painting which was invented for imbelliſhing of the face, is never named in any of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions; it ſeems that God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected this kind of diſguiſe, in that he makes no mention of it among theſe ornaments which ſerve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the beauties of his Church: Yea, this artifice is reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe of <hi>Jeſabel</hi> onely, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.30.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A moral obſervation upon <hi>Sampſon's</hi> looſing of his ſtrength and ſight, and how he recovered the one, but not the other.</head>
               <p>This ſtrong man having betrayed the honour of his <hi>Nazarites</hi> profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33453:81"/>on, the badg whereof conſiſted in his haires, loſt this prodigious ſtrength, which he kept till then, and ſo was overcome by the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> who put out his eies; after ſome time that his hairs were grown again, his ſtrength returned, but not his ſight, for he died blind: It may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded why God would reſtore him to his ſtrength which was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, but not to his ſight alſo. We might ſpeak much upon this queſtion, if here there were the place to handle what is literal in the Hiſtory. But it will ſuffice to obſerve this onely. <hi>Sampſons</hi> eyes were the cauſe of his fall; for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto his unchaſt looks many times carried him into enormous faults, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.1. into which he might have fallen again, had he recovered his ſight with his ſtrength. Which ſtrength was reſtored to him again, that he might once more chaſtiſe the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and that he might die with them: but his eies which
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33453:81"/>might have guided him out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and conducted him hither and thither as before, and would have been yet ready, to make his heart wander again after laſcivious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, were not at all reſtored to him.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="commandment">
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:33453:82"/>
            <head>The VIII. COMMANDMENT. Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why Chriſt uſed the example of theeves to induce us to ſearch for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven.</head>
               <p>HE alledgeth him who having diſcovered a treaſure in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans ground, did not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with acquaint the owner, but bought the field without giving him any ſhare of his treaſure, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.44. this is a thing diſputable; but he propoſeth alſo to us the open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of the Steward who couſned his Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and after his example he exhorts to provide for our ſalvation. Now we know well that theſe ſimilitudes tend on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to recommend wiſdom to us; but
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33453:82"/>not to approve of injuſtice: But I ask, is there no other wiſdom but that of the thief, which might ſerve us for an example to walk to heaven by? chiefly ſeeing there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lawful actions among men, which wiſdom might uſe for examples, without alledging theſe which coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance injuſtice?</p>
               <p>The intention of our Saviour in theſe ſimilitudes, is to ſhew, that to attain heaven we muſt have a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular care, and uſe extraordinary induſtry; the greatneſs of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wiſdom, could notſhew it ſelf more, then by the actions of the greateſt prudence, which can be found in the children of this world. Now among men there is commonly more prudence, ſpirit, and vivacity, and in a higher degree to be found in unlawful actions, then in thoſe which are either good, or indifferent: this is by reaſon that lawful actions conſiſt alwaies in a certain rectitude, whereas others
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33453:83"/>are full of obliquity which requires more nimbleneſs and dexterity. Now whereas this ſinful prudence makes uſe of all ſorts of means law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unlawful, in a more ſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous field, where it can extend, and put it ſelf into all poſtures, more then the wiſdom of good men can, which is ſhut up within the bounds of vertue, by reaſon man is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more ingenious to evil; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, if we would ſee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of extraordinary and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent ſubtilities, we ſhall finde them among theeves; we knowthere is nothing more inventive, then one given to this vice; for many will rob with ſuch dexterity, that the admiration they make by their induſtry, ſurmounts the diſlike we ſhould have of there iniquity; therefore the Scripture makes uſe of that ſubuject, in which it findes moſt worldly ſubtilty, to make us ſee how great the prudence of good men ſhould be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33453:83"/>
               <head>An obſervation upon this, that among Chriſt's Diſciples, there is but one no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for avarice, but all are taxed for ambition.</head>
               <p>Onely <hi>Iudas</hi> is markt out by name, and by his acts of covetouſneſs, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.6. but all the reſt are ſhewed to be ambitious; for many times they ſtrove for ſuperiority, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.46. even at that time when their Maſter was waiting for his own death, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.24. two of them made jealouſie among all the reſt, when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſit the one at Chriſts right hand, the other at his left.</p>
               <p>It ſeems that as yet ambition was more univerſal then avarice; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though both theſe are rooted in the hearts of all men, yet the one hath a more general command then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo ambition is more ancient then avarice; for ſin began at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s ambition; and in Scripture we read of many examples of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33453:84"/>which appeared in the firſt ages of the world, before we finde any examples of avarice.</p>
               <p>In brief, though both theſe be crimes, yet of the two avarice is the moſt unbeſeeming man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To one man onely God by divine means did ſhew the way to become rich</head>
               <p>It is God who ſtill giveth riches, and the lawful means to become rich. It is he alſo that giveth indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, but yet he doth not furniſh us with theſe, except by humane and natural means, which are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, diligence, experience, and other qualities; he never uſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary revelations for men to enrich themſelves, except to one man onely: this was <hi>Iacob,</hi> to whom God ſent an Angel expreſly from Heaven, to beſtow on him the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention to make himſelf rich, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.10, 11, 12. This is the onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in all the Scripture; except
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33453:84"/>we will add that of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to whom God ſhewed the means to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves by the <hi>Egyptian</hi> jewels, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.35, 36.</p>
               <p>Now it is a thing remarkable, that God hath not been ſparing of his oracles, when there hath been queſtion about providing for the neceſſities of his ſervants, or for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them advice of things requiſite to their preſervation, but to ſhew them the way to enrich themſelves, his revelations in this point have been very rare; which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in other caſes he hath not been ſparing of, as when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for the ſecurity of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; ſo he forbid <hi>Laban</hi> to wrong <hi>Iacob;</hi> or for their honour, ſo he advertiſeth <hi>Abimelech</hi> not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Wife; or for their quietneſs, ſo many times he comforteth <hi>Jacob</hi> in his afflictions; or for confirming and encouraging them in their vocations; ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he hath ſpoken to <hi>Moſes, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33453:85"/>Gedeon,</hi> and others; or for giving them victory over their enemies, ſo he ſhewed the way to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> how to ſurpriſe <hi>Hai;</hi> &amp; to <hi>David,</hi> how he might entrap the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for preventing ſome inconvenience, ſo he advertiſeth <hi>Iſaac,</hi> not to go down into <hi>Egypt;</hi> and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary he gave order to <hi>Joſeph</hi> the Husband of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, to carry Chriſt thither, that was newly born, to avoid the fury of <hi>Herod</hi>: But to teach men by oracle how to inrich themſelves, God never uſed, except one time onely, and for a ſpecial cauſe. So the Saints have ſometimes deſired revelations in caſe of neceſſity, but never for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A conjecture upon the Jewiſh opinion, touching the juſt price of things ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Rabbins</hi> teach, that he who ſells a Commodity in groſs, ought
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33453:85"/>not to gain above the fift part, that is to ſay, if the commodity hath coſt five, he may ſell it for ſix, and not above.</p>
               <p>Now I know not upon what rule or example they ground this propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it may be they have taken it from that action of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving purchaſed the property of all the Lands of <hi>Egypt</hi> contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the fifth of their yearly rent, then when he made reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his ſubjects, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.24. it may be alſo, and with more probability, that they ground this upon that law which is contented, that he who injuſtly detaines his neighbours goods, ſhould reſtore them with the addition of the fift part over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>above, <hi>Lev.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Num.</hi> 5.7.</p>
               <p>But theſe reaſons are not conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to preſcribe an univerſal price or tax; the juſtice of valuations conſiſteth not preciſely in an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome, but in a certain latitude, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſs according, to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33453:86"/>
               <head>A Queſtion: if he that hath made reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the goods unjuſtly detained, as alſo of all the profits and intereſts, and recompenced all the loſſes, hath he ſufficiently diſcharged his conſcience?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zacheus</hi> was not content to reſtore fourfold for all that he had ſtoln, but alſo he beſtowes on the poor the half of what remained of his goods lawfully gotten, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8. Now though this example doth not ſerve as a rule in all its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, yet it is founded on a rule, in reſpect of its matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>He that hath done evil is bound by the law of true repentance, to do good alſo; but this is not properly to do good, when one repairs onely the evil which he hath done; he therefore that reſtores onely what is not his own, cannot be ſaid by this action to hav don good to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; for after reſtitution of that
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33453:86"/>which he detained from another, he is bound alſo to give of his own where charity requires: the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo of his bounty muſt anſwer in ſome fit proportion, to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the robbery committed by him; for he that hath done much evil, is obliged to do alſo much good; not to pay the intereſt of Gods juſtice, which no man can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, but to expreſs the fruits of repentance, which cannot be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, if it endeavours not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the greatneſs of the evil, by the greatneſs of the good. So he that hath reſtored all, hath not as yet cleared his conſcience, becauſe for detaining another mans goods, he muſt give ſome of his own, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greatneſs and extent of the evil he had done him. He that makes reſtitution of ill gotten goods remains yet charged with great obligations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:33453:87"/>
               <head>Sacriledge the firſt crime committed in the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into <hi>Canaan.</hi> And the firſt in the Chriſtian Church.</head>
               <p>To rob God is a more hainous ſin, then to rob man; yet it is held a thing indifferent even among thoſe, who are conſcientious in all other things: yea, many there are who think it a point of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to ſuppreſs and annihilate all that their predeceſſors have conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to the ſervice of God; as though one could not be ſufficiently reformed except he commit Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: this was the firſt ſin that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> perpetrated in the land o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Promiſe, and in the firſt City they Conquered, to wit, in <hi>Ierico, Ioſh</hi> 7.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this was alſo the firſt ſin that appeared in the Chriſtian Church, committed by <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira, Acts</hi> 5.1, &amp;c. This fata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33453:87"/>ſin of the Church hath been puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both theſe beginnings, as well that of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as that of the Chriſtians, by miraculous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Judgments, to ſhew how excreable this crime is in the eyes of Almighty God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="commandment">
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:33453:88"/>
            <head>The IX. COMMANDEMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whether it be more injurious to call our neighbour fool, or knave? And why a man glorieth rather to be eſteemed good then wiſe?</head>
               <p>IT is not onely a reproach to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe wickedneſs to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but alſo to accuſe him of folly unjuſtly. Now which of theſe two kinds of calumniation be moſt cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, is a diſputable queſtion; yet a man is more ſenſible, (chiefly he that is of any ſpirit) if he be called a fool, then a wicked man. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that outwardly, &amp; in regard of inconveniences, men are more troubled if they be called wicked,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33453:88"/>yet inwardly, and in their ſecret, thoughts, they are more offended, if they be reputed fools: The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe every one naturally deſireth to be thought a man, that is a reaſonable creature, of which degree he thinks himſelf degraded, if he be taxed of folly, which is the want of judgment or reaſon, and indeed eſſentiall to man. So divine juſtice condemneth him to greater puniſhments, who calls his brother fool, then him that is angry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22.</p>
               <p>But then, how comes it, that no man (except he be a fool indeed) dare take upon him the title of wiſe; and yet every one dare call himſelf good, the cauſe alſo is plain; for though every man beleeves himſelf to be reaſonable, and is offended at the name of fool, yet he knows that the name of wiſe, includes qualities not common to all, and which are not in the power of every one, for to have a good natural underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33453:89"/>a quick apprehenſion, a good judgment, are perfections which every one cannot have, though he would never ſo fain; but to be good, that is to hav moral goodneſs, conſiſting in civil converſation only, there are none who think not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves capable thereof: therefore, as every one beleeves he may be a good man if he will, ſo every one dares call himſelf good, and that boldly, becauſe he knows that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon belief gives him power to be ſo: but as for wiſdom, which we know depends not on the will of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon, none dare ſo bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and openly aſſume this title.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An Oſervation upon this; That in the Scripture God is oftner angry with mans wickedneſs, then he uſeth to laugh at their folly.</head>
               <p>We may ſpeak the truth irronical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God himſelf uſeth ſometimes
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33453:89"/>this figure, namely, then, when he mocks Idolaters, and ſuch as truſt in Soothſayers, he invites them to try if their gods and Aſtrologers can deliver them, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.13. and then alſo when he mocks thoſe who truſt to the wiſdom or power of Kings, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.10. truly mans folly deſerveth as much to be mocked, as his malice is worthy of our indignation: yet there is oftentimes more cauſe to be angry with the wickedneſs of the world, then to laugh at its vanity. So the Scripture ſets out to us, how God is oftner angry with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of men, then he uſeth to laugh at their folly, and even then when he doth mock them, he is moſt incenſed againſt them. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:33453:90"/>
               <head>Is it lawful to divulge falſe news, if it may ſerve for the publick good?</head>
               <p>For example, to appeaſe a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented people, or to incourage them when they are affraid; or to diſperſe a tumultuous conſpiracy; or to divert the plots of an Enemy; Polititians make no ſcruple among other of their inventions to ſpread a falſe report, when they think it may produce ſome good effect: this ſeems to be countenanced by that of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> who led the <hi>Syrians</hi> into <hi>Samaria,</hi> making them beleeve, that he would conduct them elſewhere, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. but to leave the opinions of Expoſitors upon that extraordinary example; the general rule of truth is ſtill firm, for if it be not lawful to lie even for the glory of God, how much leſs for other cauſes; for is it reaſon that any eſtate, or weal pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33453:90"/>ſhould be of greater conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration with us, then God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>VVhy it is lawful ſometimes to make ſhew of evil, but never lawful to make ſhew of good.</head>
               <p>There is great odds between a formal lie, and a ſimple fiction, or reſemblance; for the one is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vitious, the other ſometimes lawful, but with a diſtinction: We do not call him an Hypocrite who makes ſhew of evil, which he hath not, but him who makes ſhew of the good he hath not; the firſt is ſometimes lawful, the other is never allowable; it is lawful for a good man to counterfeit the naughty man, as <hi>Salomon</hi> made ſhew to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch the poor infant, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> cap. 3. but it were couſnage if a wicked man ſhould counterfeit a good man; its lawful for a learned man to play the ignorant, but it were ridiculous
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33453:91"/>preſumption in an ignorant to make ſhew of learning; its lawful for a wiſe man to play the fool, as <hi>David</hi> did in the Court of <hi>Achis,</hi> but but its a trancendant folly for a fool to counterfeit the wiſe man; its lawful for a milde man to make ſhew of rigour, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to his brethren, but there is nothing more deteſtable, then for a cruel man to make ſhew of mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and laſtly, it is lawful for a friend to counterfeit the enemy, but for an enemy to play the friend, is horrible treachery.</p>
               <p>Counterfeiting therefore is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the one, but not in the other; good and evil in reſpect of their eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence lodge within man, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to outward appearance; the inſide may be good, though it doth not alwaies appear outwardly ſo, but the outſide can never be good, if there be not goodneſs within: hence it is that ſometimes good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhape of evil is lawful, but
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33453:91"/>evil is never lawful under the ſhape of good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>VVe may know a wicked man; but it is imposſible to know a good man.</head>
               <p>If I finde a man doing wickedly, I am not deceived, if I hold him for a wicked man; but when a man doth all the good he can, yet this is no infallible mark to aſſure me that he is a good man; for many do good things, either out of Hypocriſie, or ſome intereſt; ſuch will give all they have to the poor, yea, will ſuffer willingly Martyrdom, who notwithſtanding are void of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. the works they do have truly a ſuperficial goodneſs, but abuſive, becauſe the inſide is naught. As true goodneſs then lodgeth within the heart, which to us is unknown, ſo we cannot know if ſuch a man is truely good.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:33453:92"/>
               <p>But then how ſhall we know him to be wicked, ſeeing wickedneſs as wel as goodneſs hath its abode with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the heart? The reaſon of this difference is plain; an evil action never proceedes from a good heart, but an action that is outwardly good may proceed from an evil heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>When the Scripture ſpeaks of any man in Hell, it never names the man; and when it doth name him, it never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the name of Hell; an obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon this matter.</head>
               <p>The Parable in St. <hi>Luke</hi> chap. 16. nameth him who is in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, to wit, <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but gives no name to him that is in Hell! On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in general, calls him a rich man. I will omit the reaſons which ſome alledge for this, and will onely ſay, that the Scripture never nominates thoſe whom it mentioneth to be in
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33453:92"/>Hell torments; and for this cauſe it is, that the rich mans name is paſt over in ſilence, whereas <hi>Lazarus</hi> is called by his name; ſo it ſpeaks of divers ſpirits in priſon, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. that is to ſay, in Hell, but mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth none of them by name.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, when it names any that is dead in perdition, yet it never ſaith punctually, that he is in Hell; after <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traitor had hanged himſelf, the Holy Ghoſt who inſpired the Apoſtles, was not ignorant where the ſoul of that wicked wretch was; yet he ſaith nothing elſe, but that he was gone into his place, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25.</p>
               <p>Now if God himſelf who knows the names of thoſe which are in Hell, doth ſtill forbear to utter them; how much more careful ſhould we be, to refrain our ſelves in our verdicts, when we ſpeak of the ſtate and condition of thoſe who are dead; although that his
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33453:93"/>end may in ſome ſort induce us to judge ſiniſtrouſly: How raſh then are they who dare inſert into a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue the names of thoſe who are damned.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="commandment">
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:33453:93"/>
            <head>The X. COMMANDMENT. <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A ſin committed by rule and order is more enormous, then that which is done in diſorder and confuſion.</head>
               <p>A Sin that is committed with judgment, order, and formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is ſo much the more deteſtible: He that kills in cold blood, at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and with Ceremony, is more blamable, then he that kills raiſhly, and without formality: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe in the one, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding which is mans Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor acteth with complacency; but in him who is tranſported with paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it hath ſmall power: as then man is not man without underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſo it ſeems that he who offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:33453:94"/>without the concurrence of the intellect, ſhould not have his offence in ſo high a degree imputed to him: hence it is that we excuſe mad men, when in their frantick fits they commit any outrage. Briefly, the more underſtanding there is in any crime, the more enormous it is, and a ſin done orderly, is the more irregular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The diverſity of conflicts in man againſt himſelf.</head>
               <p>That which I am to ſpeak here is known ſufficiently, touching the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers conflicts that be within man: but after the deſcriptions which have been given by divers, and will be material to reduce them into a brief ſummary; now the chief combats we are to ſpeak of, be theſe.</p>
               <p>Between one Paſſion and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as ſometimes fear is oppoſite to covetouſneſs, and ſo one vice is
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33453:94"/>encountred by another, as ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſometimes reſtrained by ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, or pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Between reaſon and the paſſions, as we have a thouſand examples for this.</p>
               <p>Between reaſon and natural ſence; ſo ſome will be content to loſe an arm for the preſervation of the whole body; ſo <hi>David</hi> abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from drinking the water of <hi>Bethlem,</hi> although he was pinched with great heat and thurſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.16, 17.</p>
               <p>Between the conſcience and the will, as oftentimes the one of theſe two reſiſts the other.</p>
               <p>Between the memory and the will, as ſometimes we remember that which troubles us, and which we would willingly forget.</p>
               <p>Between reaſon and reaſon it ſelf, that is, one reaſon againſt another, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> was incloſed on both ſides, having cauſes which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to deſire a continuance of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33453:95"/>his life, and other reaſons which made him willing to forſake the world, and to be diſſolved, <hi>Phil</hi> 1.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Between ſenſe and faith; as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> having judged of things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to appearance, concluded that in vain he had waſted his heart; but faith made him retract his words, and uſe a language quite contrary, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Between natural ſenſe and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, as the Martyrs which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally abhor death, yet they received it with much alacrity; and as our Saviour expreſſing this reluctancy, ſaith to St. <hi>Peter, They will lead thee whither thou wouldſt not,</hi> John 21.18.</p>
               <p>Between the conſcience and faith; the one caſts us down by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſins before us, the other raiſeth us up, by the conſideration of Gods mercy.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, between the fleſh and the ſpirit; that is, between corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33453:95"/>nature and grace, which do ſtrive againſt each other in all the faculties of the ſoul; as truth and falſehood, juſtice and injuſtice, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and impurity. This, this is that inteſtine war, which ſets at variance the underſtanding, will, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and indeed the whole man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why ſome ſee more eaſily the defects of the memory, and of other faculties of the ſoul, then the defects of their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</head>
               <p>All unlawful deſire preſuppoſeth a corruption of judgment: if reaſon which is the eye of the ſoul were clear, all the other faculties would be pure, <hi>Matthew</hi> 6.22. but its hard for man to know when his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſtroys him, or when it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; if our memory fail in any point, we preſently take notice of this defect, and likewiſe if our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33453:96"/>be faulty: but if our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment miſcarry, it is a hard matter to find it. The reaſon of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is, becauſe it is with the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as with the eye, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things except it ſelf; our judgment judgeth of the defects which be in the other faculties of the ſoul; this is it which ſeeth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth them; but it ſeeth not its own defects except by a kinde of reflection, which is very weak and feeble; ſo that it can with facility judge of the other powers and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which are with it in man, but it can hardly judge of it ſelf; whence it comes that a fool ſeeth not his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though he ſeeth the other faults that are in him.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:33453:96"/>
            <head>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The correſpondency that is between the two Tables of the Law.</head>
               <p>THE firſt begins with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due to God, from whom we have our being.</p>
               <p>The ſecond begins at the honour due to our parents, by whom God hath given us being.</p>
               <p>The firſt forbids to make any i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God.</p>
               <p>The ſecond forbids to deface the image of God, that is, to kill men.</p>
               <p>The firſt prohibits ſpiritual adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſaying that God is jealous.</p>
               <p>The ſecond inhibits corporal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery.</p>
               <p>The firſt forbids to take Gods name in vain.</p>
               <p>The ſecond to bear falſe witneſs.</p>
               <p>The firſt commands us to labour
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:33453:97"/>ſix daies, that we may live onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our own.</p>
               <p>The ſecond prohibits to take the goods of another.</p>
               <p>The firſt commands a Sabbath or corporal reſt for our ſelves, ſervants, and cattle.</p>
               <p>The ſecond commands a reſt and contentment of ſpirit, forbidding us to covet our neighbours houſe, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and cattle.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, the ſcope of the firſt is that we love God:</p>
               <p>Of the ſecond that we love our neighbour.</p>
               <p>All theſe correſpondencies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from that which is between God and man; whence ariſe thoſe relations &amp; reſemblances which we finde between the Commandments of the firſt and ſecond Tables.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>There is love in God but not Faith and Hope.</head>
               <p>Amongſt the Prerogatives of love, above theſe other two; the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:33453:97"/>Logical vertues, this is conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that God loveth, but he doth not beleeve nor hope; for to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve is an act of Faith, which is of things unſeen. But what is ther that God ſeeth not? and beſides, what can be wanting to him, that he ſhould ſtand in need of hope; theſe two vertues are imcompatible with an infinite perfection. This is then one of the preheminences of love, in that it is found in God; yea, God himſelf is called <hi>Love,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16. and in this reſpect it is greater then Faith and Hope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whether it is a greater defect, to want Faith or Charity?</head>
               <p>This queſtion depends upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> which of theſe two is the moſt difficult, to wit Faith or Charity? For though both the one and the other be the gifts of God, yet the one may be more hard and difficult to us, then the other.
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33453:98"/>Now though theſe two vertues are ſtill together, (ſeeing it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the one to be without the other) yet they are not alwaies equal, and in the ſame degree; the more common act of theſe two is charity; for we ſee more examples of love then of faith: many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians love God earneſtly, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding have much difficulty to aſſure themſelves of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>One cauſe that makes the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of love, more eaſie then thoſe of faith is, for that the objects of love are more intelligible and percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our underſtanding; for love hath for its object the goodneſs of God, but faith hath for its object, his truth: now it is more eaſie for us to conceive that God is good, then to underſtand how he is true, in all points which appear not to us; and yet we are commanded to beleeve. As then the motion of faith is more difficult then that of love; ſo he
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33453:98"/>that wants the acts of charity is more blameable, then he who is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the acts of faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In all the Hiſtory of that time which was before the law, the love of God was never mentioned in expreſs termes, but onely the fear of God.</head>
               <p>From the Creation till the Law, are reckoned twenty five thouſand years, in which great interval of ages, were many Patriarchs, and other perſons famous for piety; to whom God ſpake many times, and in divers manners. The ſacred ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie marks out their vertues, and names the fear of God, as the moſt excellent amongſt them, but never expreſſeth their love towards God; its true, that this fear or reverence was not without a true divine love, yet they are diſtinct qualities; the one of which is named, but we never read of the other. <hi>Abraham</hi> being in <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> ſaid, <hi>That in that place the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33453:99"/>fear of God was not.</hi> Gen. 20.11. <hi>Jacob</hi> ſwore by the fear of <hi>Iſaac</hi> his father, that is to ſay, by the name of the ſame God whom <hi>Iſaac</hi> feared, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.53. <hi>Joſeph</hi> confeſſed he feared God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.18. the midwives of <hi>Egypt</hi> are commended for fearing God, <hi>Exodus</hi> 1.17.21. In brief, before the Law was publiſhed, Religion and Piety was expreſſed by the name of <hi>the Fear of God,</hi> and not by that of <hi>the Love of God;</hi> and it is obſervable that the action of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in offering his ſon for a burnt ſacrifice, whereby he did ſo highly witneſs his love to God, this action, I ſay, is aſcribed to his fear of God, without mentioning the love which he had ſhewed to him, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 22.12. the firſt time that ever the Scripture did expreſs this phraſe, of <hi>the Love of God,</hi> was after the repetition of the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5.</p>
               <p>Now why the name of this great vertue was not uttered but after a long time, and frequent mention of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:33453:99"/>the fear of God? Seems to proceed from this, that among the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, the firſt which he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to man, (as I obſerved upon the Creed) was his power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Romans</hi> 1.20. So when our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding deſires to know what the Divinity is, by this word, it conceives a power eminent above all others: this is the firſt thought we have of this ſubject; whence it followeth, that the firſt impreſſion it makes in man, after he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to know God, is the fear which this ſupreme power gives to the ſoul; and becauſe this fear is the firſt motive by which man is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſubmit himſelf to God; hence it is, that in the holy ſong, all religious affections have been compriſed under the name of <hi>the fear of God;</hi> and for this cauſe this <hi>Fear</hi> was for a long time named, without mentioning expreſly or particularly, <hi>the Love of God;</hi> but when the wiſdom of God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33453:100"/>large inſtructions under the Law, it afterward expreſſed the commandment of loving God, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing the ſame Love from Fear, <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 10.12. What is it that the Lord thy God requireth, but that thou Fear him, and Love him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of them who excuſe their faults on this: That God hath not given them more underſtanding and judgement.</head>
               <p>Theſe men willing to excuſe themſelves, accuſe God, as if their faults were to be imputed to him: whereas on the contrary, the whole fault is in themſelves; the Law wils that we love God with all our mind; thou alledgeth, thou haſt but little minde; but how little ſoever it be, haſt thou imployed it all in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and love of God? Truly, there is no man that hath lived according to the meaſure and proportion of that underſtanding and judgment
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33453:100"/>God hath given him. In brief, if a fool excuſe himſelf on this, that God hath not given him more under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; a wicked man will excuſe himſelf on this, that God hath not given him more goodneſs: for this is a gift of God, as well as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In the duties of man towards God, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfullneſs is more culpable then igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</head>
               <p>When we ſpeak of divine things, many complain that they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them in their memory, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect whereof they accuſe; but they think not how forgetfullneſs is a ſin, ſeeing the love of God requires a concurrence of all the faculties of our ſouls, among which memory is one: the defect of which is not a ſimple infirmity, as the vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple uſeth to qualifie it; but ſuch a defect, as ſhould be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſins of omiſſion, then
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33453:101"/>when it imports a remembrance of a conſiderable point, though it be not neceſſary, nor poſſible to retain all the ſyllables in which it hath been pronounced or written. As he who forgets God is more crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, then he that never knew God; even ſo he who looſeth a leſſon which hath been taught him, is more culpable then he that never learned it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:33453:101"/>
            <head>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Whence comes it, that contrary to all other affections, this which man carries to himſelf, hath no bounds; and why this never faileth, nor is ſubject to diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</head>
               <p>In the affections we have towards another, we feel and know even to what degree we love him, more or leſs; but no man can tell to what hight he loves himſelf; for this love hath no bounds but runs <hi>in infinitum.</hi> Moreover the affection that one bears to another, may be leſſened or interrupted, or quite annihilated, yet turned into hatred; but the love he bears to himſelf is never blotted out, nor is it diminiſhed, though never ſo little.</p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:33453:102"/>
               <p>Among the reaſons of this diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, we may produce this: between every one of us and another, there are differences of proximity: our affections move within theſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals which have their meaſures and degrees. Now within theſe diſtances many cauſes of diverſion or averſion may intervene, which intercept or turn aſide the affections; but as there is no diſtance between a man and himſelf, even ſo the love which a man bears to himſelf, it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately faſtens to its object; ſo that between the one and the other, there is no place that can admit the interpoſition of any contrary cauſe, the affection we bear to another moveth out of it ſelf, but that which each man hath to himſelf, moveth as it were in a circle continually round about it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:33453:102"/>
               <head>Why the older we grow, the more we love our ſelves?</head>
               <p>It is hard to beleeve that this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural love wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> every one bears to himſelf, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> born with us can receive any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ment, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready great, and of a high ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, even when we are as yet in the Cradle: ſome will ſay then, that nothing can be added to ſuch an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſeeing it is ſo great in its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning: But on the other ſide, it ſeemeth that it increaſeth ſtill, and gathers ſtrength and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, as man increaſeth in years: in witneſs whereof, we may alledge that ordinarily a father doth more love thoſe children which are born to him in his old age, then thoſe he had before; as <hi>Jacob</hi> was more tender over <hi>Benjamin,</hi> then over the reſt of his children: I know other reaſons may be given for this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of affection; but perhaps
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33453:103"/>they proceed alſo from this cauſe: Though all the children of one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are his fleſh and blood, yet notwithſtanding the fathers affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards himſelf being greater in his old age, then before; this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends alſo in a greater meaſure, towards thoſe children which he begets in that age.</p>
               <p>But there is another probability that ſheweth the increaſe of mens affections to themſelves with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of their age; as long famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity increaſeth the love that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two perſons; ſo that man, that hath been long converſant with himſelf, &amp; hath had long experience of his own fidelity, and confident in his own directions, hath reaſon to love himſelf more then before, ſeeing he was not then ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:33453:103"/>
               <head>VVhy we do not envy another mans good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</head>
               <p>He that loves his neighbour as himſelf, will never envy him: for this vice is incompatible with love, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. It may be asked then, why men do envy the greatneſs, riches, knowledge, ingenuity, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and other qualities of their neighbours, but are never envious of their goodneſs, and piety? for ſome will envy a man becauſe he is in honor, or becauſe he is rich, or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, or eloquent; but they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver envy a man becauſe he is good.</p>
               <p>This proceeds from divers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either from the ſmall eſteem that men have of goodneſs, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of other things; or from this, that every one perſwades him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he can when he pleaſeth be as good as another; or from this, that goodneſs is ſo oppoſite
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33453:104"/>to envy formally, that it cannot be envies object, being ſo contrary to it; we cannot envy that in another, which we cannot deſire for our ſelves.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:33453:104"/>
            <head>Divers Duties of the Law.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Concluſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why <hi>Moſes</hi> who wrought ſo great and many miracles, never raiſed any from the dead?</head>
               <p>HE that turned the waters into blood, who made fire and ſtorms fall upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> who divided the ſea, and drew water out of the rocks; who wrought ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miracles upon all the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet never reſtored any dead to life. If one ask the reaſon, why this kinde of miracle was not found among theſe other ſupernatural acts, which made the Lawgiver ſo famous? It wil be anſwered by ſom, that this queſtion is either unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable or unprofitable, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33453:105"/>it is conſiderable, and the ſolution is ſufficiently clear: for this anſwereth the quality of the law, which was given by <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Law conſidered without Chriſt, is a letter that killeth; and the miniſtry of <hi>Moſes,</hi> is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of death. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7. his office was not to give life, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to take it a way; in teſtimony of which, and to ſhew that the life and reſurection is to be ſought for elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, then in the Moſaical Law; <hi>Moſes</hi> never received power to raiſe any from the dead, although there wanted not occaſions, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to invite him to produce this miracle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Law continued from <hi>Moſes,</hi> who had an impediment in his ſpeech, till <hi>John</hi> the ſon of <hi>Zachary,</hi> which <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> was ſpeechleſs, <hi>Luk. 16.16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It were needleſs to ſpeak of that again which is ſo well known, to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33453:105"/>wit, in what regard the Law was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, and in what reſpect it yet continues? The Oeconomy of the Old Teſtament, chiefly ſince <hi>Moſes</hi> required the obſervation of the Law, as a means to obtain juſtice and life by, if men did fulfil it; and notwithſtanding it made them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that by reaſon of their ſins, the Law could not pronounce them juſt, being in this regard im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, and having its mouth ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p>This ſeems to have been myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally intimated, as well in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as towards the end of that le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Oeconomy; to introduce the Law, God made uſe of a man, who had an impediment in his ſpeech; for when <hi>Moſes</hi> was injoyned to go to <hi>Pharoah,</hi> he excuſeth himſelf, by reaſon of his defect of ſpeech, <hi>Exodus</hi> 4.10. And to ſignifie the abolition of the Law, then when its time was almoſt expired, to make way for a more perfect Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33453:106"/>God made the legal Prieſts, dumb, who laſt his ſpeech in the very Temple, and at the time he ſhould have pronounced the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on the people, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.20, 21.22. thus the Law as well at its entry, as at its departure, hath ſhewed, that it cannot bring us that great benefit of juſtification with a full mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why God in ſpeaking to man, uſeth more words, then when he is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpeaking to the creatures which want underſtanding; and why he uſeth ſo many words and repetitions to effect mans converſation, ſeeing he can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him, with one word onely.</head>
               <p>God hath ſomtimes ſpoken, or cauſed ſpeeches to be utterred to the creatures, which want either underſtanding or ears: He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Sun and Moon to ſtand ſtill, the Sea and Windes to be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, the Whale that it ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33453:106"/>
                  <hi>Jonas,</hi> and the Feavers that they ſhould be gone; to obtain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience from them, he ſpoke to them but one word, and the effect was as ready as the command, for Heaven, Earth, Elements, Plants, and the beaſts know the voice of their Soveraign Lord, and ſubmit themſelves to it without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but whereas man is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refractory, and oppoſeth himſelf to the will of God, he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſpeak to him in few words what his pleaſure is, but incourageth him with reaſons, which he cleareth and inculcateth, and withal adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth promiſes and menaces.</p>
               <p>Surely God could effect by one word onely, that for which he uſeth ſuch long remonſtrances; he makes himſelf to be obeyed ſometimes, in ſaying onely <hi>fellow me;</hi> but to make men know how far they are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him, and how difficult their converſion is; ordinarly he doth not make them draw nigh to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33453:107"/>him, but by degrees ſlowly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many ſummons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>VVhy the Scripture ſpeaking of Vertue and Vice, doth command or prohibit one oftner then another.</head>
               <p>For Example; it ſpeaketh oftner againſt avarice, then againſt prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, though it condemneth both. So againſt exceſſive care oftner then againſt negligence; and ſo likewiſe it oftner recommends to us liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then frugality, though it mention both; the reaſon is plain enough, becauſe avarice is more general then prodigality; and on the other ſide there be more frugal then libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral men: therefore the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a vice is, the oftner it ſhould be cryed down: on the contrary, a vertue which is found but ſeldom; ought to be the oftner recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>We could produce many other paſſages upon theſe Subjects of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:33453:107"/>Vertue and Vice; but ſeeing we have undertaken onely theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations which concern the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue in general, in each one of the Commandments; I paſs to theſe which I am to handle upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
